<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meditations and disquisitions, upon the seven psalmes of David, commonly called the penitentiall Psalmes Namely, The 6. The 32. The 38. The 51. The 102. The 130. The 143. By Sir Richard Baker knight.</title>
            <title>Meditations and disquisitions upon the seven penitentiall psalmes</title>
            <author>Baker, Richard, Sir, 1568-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113582</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848815</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848815</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13931</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02139)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13931)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 693:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meditations and disquisitions, upon the seven psalmes of David, commonly called the penitentiall Psalmes Namely, The 6. The 32. The 38. The 51. The 102. The 130. The 143. By Sir Richard Baker knight.</title>
                  <title>Meditations and disquisitions upon the seven penitentiall psalmes</title>
                  <author>Baker, Richard, Sir, 1568-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 99, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Francis Eglesfield, and are to be sold at the signe of the Mary-gold in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An issue, with cancel title page and different imprint, of: Baker, Richard.  Meditations and disquisitions upon the seven penitentiall psalmes.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, title page has "psalmes"; a variant has "Psalmes".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13931:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13931:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEDITATIONS AND DISQVISITIONS, UPON The Seven pſalmes of DAVID, commonly called the Penitentiall PSALMES.</p>
            <p>NAMELY,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 32.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 38.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 51.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 102.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 130.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 143.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Sir</hi> RICHARD BAKER <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I.D.</hi> for <hi>Francis Eglesfield,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Mary-gold in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13931:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13931:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE MARY, Counteſſe of DORSET; the Vertuous Lady, of the Right Honourable, <hi>Edward</hi> Earle of DORSET.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Lady; It is not the leaſt of your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that you are not proud of your Vertues; which, if it
<pb facs="tcp:13931:3"/>had beene in the Angells that fell, they had perhaps not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len. And becauſe you delight ſo much in Humbleneſſe; It makes mee bold to Preſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, theſe Pſalmes of <hi>Davids</hi> Humiliation. How happie were I, if I could make a Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, anſwerable to <hi>Davids</hi> plaine ſong: but what is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in mine, your owne Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations will happily ſupply; which cannot but be excellent, being followed by the practice of ſo Vertuous a life; of which I wiſh I could as well make a Monument to remaine to all Poſteritie, for their Example; as it will certainly remaine to your owne Poſteritie, for their
<pb facs="tcp:13931:3"/>glory. But leaſt I ſhould adde the offence of tediouſneſſe to boldneſſe: I humbly crave par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for having ſaid ſo much; but more, for having ſayd no more; and make it my aſpiring ſuite to bee accounted as I truly am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips devoted Servant, <hi>RICHARD BAKER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:13931:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Recenſui Meditationes has in Septem Pſalmos Davidis, &amp; Typis mandari permitto.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SAMVEL BAKER.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex Aedibus Londinenſ:</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iunii</hi> 5. 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13931:4"/>
            <head>THE SIXTH PSALME.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord rebuke me not in thine anger, neither chaſten mee in thy heavie diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Have mercie upon me, O Lord, for I am weake; Heale mee, for my bones are troubled.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> My Soule alſo is troubled, but thou, O Lord, how long?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Returne, O Lord, and deliver my Soule; ſave me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> For in Death there is no remembrance of thee; and who ſhall praiſe thee in the Grave?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> I am weary with my ſighing; all the night make I my bed to ſwimme; I water my couch with my teares.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Mine eye is conſumed becauſe of griefe; and is waxen old becauſe of all mine enemies.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13931:5"/> 
               <hi>8</hi> Depart from mee all ye workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tte; for the Lord hath heard the voyce of my wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> The Lord hath heard my ſupplication; the Lord hath received my prayer.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Let all mine enemies be aſhamed and ſore vexed, Let them turne their backes and bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, ſuddenly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13931:5"/>
            <head>MEDITATIONS And diſquiſitions upon the Sixth <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> My ſoule, what is it thou haſt done? haſt thou beene ſtriving with the Angell, about the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of <hi>Moſes?</hi> For why elſe ſhouldſt thou bee afraid of the Angels imprecation to Sathan, when hee ſtrove with him about it, The Lord rebuke thee? Certainly either the Angel was very milde in his imprecation, or thou art very ſharp in thy deprecation. But O wretch that I am! If Sathan deſerved rebuking for ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with an Angel; how much more do I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, for ſtriving with the Creator of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? and not about taking away the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but about taking away the glory of his holy Name? For ſuch, and ſo execrable are my ſinnes, that through them, the holineſſe of Gods glorious name is blaſphemed among the Gentiles. And have I not juſt cauſe then to feare that he will, and therefore juſt cauſe to pray, that he will not, Rebuke me in his anger, nor chaſten mee in his heavy diſpleaſure.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13931:6"/>
            <p> But though rebuking were an imprecation to Sathan, yet to mee it is not ſo, ſeeing I doe not more deſerve it, then I need it; as I deſerve it for my ſin, ſo I need it for my amendment: for without rebuking, what amending? what amending indeed without thy rebuking? For alas, the fleſh flatters mee, the world abuſeth mee, Sathan deludes mee; and now O God, if thou alſo ſhouldſt hold thy peace, and wink at my follies, whom ſhould I have? Alas, whom could I have, to make mee ſenſible of their fouleneſſe. If thou ſhouldſt not tell mee, and tell me roundly, I went a ſtray, how ſhould I ever, alas, how could I ever be brought to returne into the right way? To thy rebuking therefore I humbly ſubmit my ſelfe; I know thou intendeſt it for my amendment, and not for my confuſion; for my converſion, and not for my ſubverſion: It may be bitter in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, but is moſt comfortable in the working: hard perhaps to digeſt, but moſt ſoveraigne, being digeſted: Yet I cannot endure thou ſhouldſt rebuke mee in anger, I cannot endure it in affection, but I can leſſe endure it in abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: It is grievous to mee, to thinke thou art angry, but it is inſupportable to mee, to feele thou art angry: the hand of thine anger is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, and though of thy ſelfe thou be as it were a ſweetly breathing ayre; yet anger maks thee a conſuming fire, that if thine anger be kindled, yea, but a little, Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in thee.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13931:6"/>
            <p> When I conſider with my ſelfe the many favours, undeſerved favours, thou haſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed unto mee, and conſider withall, how little uſe, how ill uſe I have made of them all, though I know I have juſtly deſerved thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking, yet my hope is ſtill, thou wilt adde this favour alſo, not to rebuke me in thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: but when I thinke, how unkinde a thing thy rebuking is, but how terrible a thing thine anger is; when I thinke, what a paine it is to have thee chaſten mee, but what a death it is, to have thee chaſten mee in diſpleaſure; then I fall a trembling in all my joynts, and never think I can make haſte enough to ſay, and to ſay with ſighing; O Lord, rebuke mee not in thine anger, neither chaſten mee in thy heavie diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>But why may not God rebuke mee, as <hi>Eli</hi> rebuked his ſonnes? for hee rebuked his ſons for their ſinnes, and yet no anger appeared in him at all. O my ſoule, wilt thou make <hi>Eli</hi> a pattern for God? becauſe God is a loving Father, wilt thou therefore make him like <hi>Eli,</hi> too indulgent a father? <hi>Ely</hi> indeed rebuked his ſonnes with a rod, but hee made his rod of Roſes and Violets: hee rebuked them for ſins of preſumption, as if they had been but ſins of infirmity: hee rebuked them for ſinnes of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, as if they had beene but ſinnes of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: and what was this, but inſtead of ſtriking them, to ſtroake them, and inſtead of ſtopping them in their race, to adde rather a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13931:7"/>ſpurre unto them? And was it not for this, that God rebuked <hi>Eli</hi> in his anger, becauſe <hi>Eli</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked not his ſonnes in his anger? I deny not O God, but that my ſinnes deſerve thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; or rather I acknowledge they juſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke thine anger: but alas, O Lord, if thou ſhouldeſt enter into judgement with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, what fleſh were able to ſtand before thee, and not bee conſumed? O vile ſinne of mine, enough to put patience it ſelfe into cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, able to anger a ſaint, nay, even the King of ſaints. That if thou O God, ſhouldeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke mee in thine anger, if chaſten mee in thy heavie diſpleaſure, I could not ſay, but that thine anger were lenitie, and thy diſpleaſure, mildneſſe.</p>
            <p>But what boldneſſe of language is this in ſpeaking to God? am I not worthy of rebuke, for praying God, not to rebuke mee in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as though I thought that God could bee angry? For, is not anger a paſſion of humane infirmitie, and will I make God ſubject to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of infirmitie? Is not anger a defect in reaſon is? not God a perfection above reaſon? and can there bee defect in perfection? can there bee paſſion in him, that is <hi>Purus Actus?</hi> But is it not, that anger in God is not a paſſion, but an action, not a defect, but an effect: for then is God ſayd to bee angry, when he puts his judgements in execution, when his rebukings tend not to converſion, but to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: when his mercy attempers not the rigour
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13931:7"/>of his juſtice. Oh then, rebuke mee O God, but not in thine anger; rebuke me as thou didſt the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> who at thy rebuking repented and were converted: but rebuke mee not as thou didſt <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who hardned his heart at thy rebuking, and was confounded. If thou O God, ſhouldſt rebuke mee in thine anger, I ſhould more have an eye to thy rod, then give an eare to thy leſſon: I ſhould bee more terrified with thine anger, then edified with thy rebuking, and ſhould be made unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of thy doctrine, with the terror of thy teaching: for I, alas, am as a nayle under the workmans hammer, better driven in with gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſtroakes, then with hard blowes: Oh ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, rebuke mee not O God, if thou be angry, or if thou rebuke mee, bee not angry: Two ſuch ſharp notes, as anger and rebuking are, can never make any pleaſing muſicke, if they meet together. Anger in rebuking, makes the water troubled, and thick that ſhould be drunk cleere, makes the Ayre ſultry, and hot, that ſhould be breathed in cold, extremely both of them unwholeſome for the body: and ſeeing thou intendeſt my health, and ſeekeſt not to make mee ſicke, Let not anger enflame thy rebuking O God, that ſo the ayre of it I may take in the cooler, that ſo the water of it I may drink the cleerer. I, alas, am as a narrow mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed veſſell in the hand of the drawer, better filled with ſoftly pouring in, then with pouring in haſtily, which commonly ſpills more then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13931:8"/>it fills: and ſeeing thy rebuking is too precious a liquor to bee ſpilt, O poure it in with the ſoftly hand of patience, and not with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hand of anger; that ſo it may the ſooner fil, &amp; the better enter without ſpilling, into this narrow mouthed veſſell of my emptie ſoule. Thy rebuking O God, is to mee as thunder, but thine anger is as lightning: and is it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that thou terrifie my ſoule with the thunder of thy rebuking, but thou wilt alſo ſet this flaxe of my fleſh on fire with the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thine anger? Thy rebuking of it ſelfe is a precious Balme, but mixt with anger, turns to a Corroſive: O keepe thy Corroſives, O God, for ſuch hardned hearts as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> was; Apply to mee onely the ſimple Balme of thy rebuking, and let it not have any mixture at all of thy Corroding anger in it. What though I have offended thee with ſins of anger, muſt thou needs take revenge, in the ſame kind thou art offended? and if needs thou muſt doe ſo, why maiſt thou not then take revenge of my ſinnes in thy good pleaſure, ſeeing I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended thee as much with ſinnes of pleaſure? Thou didſt walke in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> with our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, in the coole of the day, when the heate of the ſunne was over, and this made thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence as cheerfull, as glorious: Vouchſafe O God, to deale ſo with mee, rebuke mee in the coole of thy Spirit, when the heat of thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is over-paſt; for elſe alas, it may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but can never be comfortable.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13931:8"/>
            <p> But if rebuking me in thine anger, be ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Potion, what is it then, to chaſten mee in thine indignation? for where the worſt of thy rebuking in anger, is but threatning of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the beſt of thy chaſtening in indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is inflicting of puniſhment: and though a ſtrong heart may perhaps endure ſuch threatnings, yet no ſtrength of heart is able to beare ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictings. It is terror enough to heare thee but chide, but to feele thee ſtrike, and that with ſtroakes of indignation, what power of any creature is able to endure it? I aske not, thou wouldſt not chaſten mee: this were to aske, thou wouldſt not love mee; for whom thou loveſt, thou chaſteneſt; and would I loſe thy love, for any chaſtening? O gracious God, chaſten mee in what manner, with what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thou pleaſeſt: chaſten mee as thou didſt <hi>Lazarus,</hi> by making him lye for hunger at <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves</hi> gate: chaſten me as thou didſt <hi>Iob,</hi> by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him lye with ſores upon the dunghill: chaſten mee, as thou didſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> by making him bee caſt into the Lions denne: but then chaſten me in love, and not in indignation; for thy chaſtening in love, though it paine, yet it heales; though it bruiſe, yet it comforts: Thy rod &amp; thy ſtaff, they comfort me; but thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening in indignation, is paine without hope, is bruiſing in deſpaire, or rather not a paine but a torment, not a bruiſing, but a breaking: that no miſery can bee comparable to this chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to be chaſtened in thine indignation.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13931:9"/>
            <p> Chaſtening and love may well bee matcht together, they are like to <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Rachel,</hi> though there be ſeven yeares of ſervice more, yet <hi>Rachel</hi> will bee had at laſt: but chaſtening and indignation are as badly matcht as may bee, for chaſtening enclines to converſion, and indignation is wholy bent upon confuſion; oh therefore, match thy chaſtening with love, and not with indignation, that ſo, at leaſt, I may come at laſt, to enjoy my <hi>Rachel,</hi> that is, thy favour: Chaſtening and love, may lodge both together in the bowels of a father, but indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation comes not where bowels are: and how then, O God, canſt thou chaſten me in indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but thou muſt as it were disbowell thy ſelfe, and utterly abandon the name of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? and ſhall any thing make thee to leave that Name? I know, O God, it is a name ſo deare unto thee, that I hope I ſhall commit no ſuch ſinne; and ſuffer mee not O God, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any ſuch ſinne as ſhall ever be able to make thee abandon it. Indeed here, where wee call thee Lord, indignation may appeare, and bee bold to ſhew it ſelfe: but when wee come to name thee Father, indignation muſt be gone, and never preſume to come in place. If thy chaſtening bee intended for reforming, or for poliſhing, what wouldſt thou doe with indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that tends to aboliſhing? And if thou chaſten whom thou loveſt, and then deſtroy whom thou chaſteneſt; what difference will there bee betweene thy indignation, and thy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13931:9"/>mercy? Oh let not thy chaſtening, which is ordained to be a rod for thy children, be made a knife to ſlaughter thy Children: Conſider, O God, I am but a pot made of brittle Clay, that if thy hand hold not a temper in ſtriking, I ſhall ſoone bee broken, and beaten in pieces, and then thy workmanſhip will bee defaced. And ſhall it ever bee ſayd of thee, that with one hand thou makeſt, and with the other hand deſtroyeſt? Remember O God, whoſe title it is, to bee a deſtroyer: thy title is to bee a Creator: and ſhall I finde no more favour at the hands of a Creator, then I might looke to finde at the hands of a deſtroyer?</p>
            <p>Alas, my ſoule, I know full well, it were a grievous caſe for mee, if God ſhould let his chaſtening and his indignation joyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and aſſayle mee with them both at once; but how ſhall I doe to keepe them aſunder? Have I any <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſtand for mee in the gap? Bleſſed be thy glorious Name, O God: I have indeed a greater then <hi>Moſes,</hi> even him, whom thou didſt chaſten in thy heavie diſpleaſure; to the end thou mightſt not chaſten mee in thy heavie diſpleaſure; for his agonie of crying, My God, My God, why haſt thou forſaken mee; gives mee boldneſſe to cry, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in crying, My God, My God, have mercy upon mee: This I know will helpe, when all other helps ſayle. But what have I in my ſelfe to plead, why God ſhould not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten mee in his heavie diſpleaſure? Can I ſay,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13931:10"/>I have not deſerved it? Or can I ſay I have not even provoked him to doe it? Alas, O God, I have nothing in thee to flie to, but onely thy mercy; nothing in my ſelfe to plead, but onely my weakneſſe; Have mercy upon mee, O God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> for I am weake.</p>
            <p>But is not this a weak Plea, to alleage weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for a Plea? weak indeed with men, who commonly tread hardeſt upon the weakeſt, and are ever going over where the hedge is loweſt; but no weake Plea with God, whoſe mercy is ever readie upon all occaſions, and then moſt, when there is moſt need: and ſeeing there is greateſt need, where there is greateſt weakneſſe, therefore no Plea with God ſo ſtrong as this; Have mercy upon me, O God, for I am weake.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould <hi>David</hi> pray for mercy to helpe his weakneſſe? for what can mercy do? Mercy can but pitty his weaknes, it is ſtrength that muſt relieve it. But is it not, that mercy, I may ſay, is as the ſteward of Gods houſe, and hath the command of all he hath: that if wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be wanting for direction, mercy can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it. If juſtice be wanting for defence, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy can obtain it: If ſtrength be wanting for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, Mercy can command it: and therefore no Plea ſo perfect to bee urged with God, as this, Have mercy upon mee, O God, for I am weake.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould <hi>David</hi> make his weakneſſe a motive to God for mercy? for is not weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13931:10"/>an effect of ſinne? and can God love the effect, when hee hates the cauſe? but it is not the weakeneſſe in <hi>David</hi> that God loves, but the acknowledging of his weakneſſe: for what is this, but the true humility? and who knowes not in how high account ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is with God, ſeeing it is indeed of this wonderfull condition, that though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be ſo low, yet nothing reacheth ſo high, and therefore no motive ſo fit to move God, as this; Have mercy upon mee, O God, for I am weake. Mercy indeed looks downe upon no object ſo directly, as upon weakeneſſe; and weakeneſſe lookes up to no object ſo directly as to mercy: and therefore they cannot chuſe but meete, and meeting, not chuſe but embrace each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Mercy, weakneſſe as her Clyent: weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Mercy as her Patron: that no Plea can bee with God ſo ſtrong, as this, Have mercy upon mee, O God, for I am weake. Let thy indignation, O God, be layd upon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and ſuch as truſt in their ſtrength, for upon them thou maiſt get thee honour: but alas, what honour can bee gotten, by pouring thy indignation upon ſo weake a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as I am? Thy honour ſhall bee as much to ſupport my weakneſſe by thy mercy; as to abate their pride, by thine indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But what though <hi>David</hi> be weak? is every weaknes ſufficient cauſe to run to God about?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13931:11"/>might he not take Reſtoratives and Cordialls, and ſuch other comfortable things, and ſo help his weakneſſe without going to God? O my ſoule, what comfort is in a Cordiall, if it be not of Gods making? what ſtrength in a Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, if it be not of Gods giving? No, O Lord, thy mercy is the only reſtorative that can help my weakneſſe; the true <hi>Aqua Coeleſtis,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſpirits.</p>
            <p>I know, O God, thou ſweetly diſpoſeſt all things both in weight and meaſure; Thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereſt man that he is but duſt; Thou knoweſt mee, that I am a worme, and no man; and can it then be thou ſhouldſt have no conſideration of my weakneſſe? wilt thou not proportion thy burthen to the bearer? wilt thou loade a Gnat, as thou wouldſt loade a Camell? Oh have mercy upon mee, O God, and conſider my weakneſſe, for I am weake.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould <hi>David</hi> make his weakneſſe; a cauſe for God to ſpare him? for how came hee by his weakneſſe? was it not by his owne diſorder? and then, if his weakneſſe be one of his faults, hath not God juſt cauſe to ſtrike him the harder for his weakneſſe? It ſeemes, indeed, that <hi>David</hi> cannot deny but that he deſerves it, and therefore layes not his Plea in the Court of Gods juſtice, but of his mercy; for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, he knoweth, hath bowells of compaſſion, and will not alwaies bee ruled by rigour; but finding contrition, will have a regard of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And indeed, ſeeing the end of Gods
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13931:11"/>chaſtening is but to piece up my breaches, why ſhould hee ſtrike ſo hard, to break mee in pieces.</p>
            <p>But are there not ſome men, that feign them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be ſelves poore, when yet they be rich, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would pay but a little tribute? And may not <hi>David</hi> be ſuch a one, feign himſelfe to bee weake, when perhaps hee was ſtrong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee would have God to ſpare him in his chaſtening? But never have ſuch a thought of <hi>David:</hi> for heare him what hee ſayes farther: Heale mee, for my bones are troubled, and ſurely, if his bones bee troubled, hee may well bee allowed to ſay hee is weake. For if there be any ſtrength in our bodies, it is in our bones: they are both ableſt to withſtand harme, and fartheſt removed out of harmes way; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any trouble can come to them, it muſt paſſe the skinne, the fleſh, the membranes, and all other parts, that if once the bones come to bee troubled, wee may juſtly ſay, <hi>Res rediit ad Triarios,</hi> the matter is come to the height of extremity: And therefore, <hi>David</hi> finding trouble in his bones, had juſt cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of weakneſſe, and to ſay; Heale mee, O God, for my bones are troubled. Diſtempers and infirmities are ever more hard, or eaſie to be cured, as they are ſeated in parts, more hard or eaſie to be wrought upon: and therefore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers in the ſpirits, are of al other the eaſieſt to be cured, more hard in the humours, but in the ſolid parts hardeſt of all, for then they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13931:12"/>grow to bee Hectick; and ſuch, in all account, are ſcarſe held curable: and ſeeing of all the ſolid parts the bones are the moſt ſolid, and therefore diſeaſes in them the hardeſt to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; <hi>David</hi> had juſt cauſe to call to God for helpe, and to ſay; Heale mee, O God, for my bones are troubled. If the beames of a houſe bee unſound and ſhaken, how is it poſſible the houſe ſhould ſtand, and as little is it poſſible, that this body of mine ſhould bee ſaved from ruine: if my bones which are the beams of it, be out of order, and troubled.</p>
            <p>But if the trouble of the bones be ſo incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is it not preſumption in <hi>David</hi> to ſay; Heale me, O God, for my bones are troubled: being as if he ſhould ſay, cure me, O God, for I am paſt all cure, and ſo tempt God, with deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to do a worke that is impoſſible? But is it not, that <hi>David</hi> knowes to whom hee ſpeakes? hee knowes hee ſpeaks not to <hi>Galen,</hi> or to <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> hee knowes hee ſpeakes not to <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> or to <hi>Apollo,</hi> but hee ſpeakes to him that is a tranſcendent to all theſe: One to whom, not only nothing is impoſſible, but to whom all impoſſible things are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. It were indeed an unreaſonable requeſt in the eye of Nature, but very unreaſonable in the eye of Faith: ſeeing Faith indeed is then moſt reaſonable, when moſt it is above all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; which therefore-made <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the faithfull, becauſe contrary to hope, hee believed in hope, that God would
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13931:12"/>make him ſuch a father. And indeed moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly then it growes to bee a cure for God, when in mans judgement it is growne incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: as Chriſt would not go to heale <hi>Lazarus</hi> untill hee was dead, and had beene foure daies buried, thereby perhaps to prepare beliefe for his owne reſurrection: ſeeing it might well bee believed hee could riſe himſelfe the third day, who had raiſed another after foure daies. Never therefore fear, my ſoule, to ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Heale me, for my bones are troubled: for the time will come, when hee ſhall heale thee, not onely when thy bones bee troubled, but when they bee mouldred away into duſt and powder: for even then hee will gather them together againe, and make them ſtand up, and ſerve for beams to this bodie of thine, as now they doe.</p>
            <p>But how can the bones bee troubled, ſeeing they have no ſenſe? for it is the fleſh and the membranes that feele the pain, the bones feele none. Oh then conſider how great my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is, which ſtrikes a ſenſe of paine into my very parts that are not ſenſible.</p>
            <p>And now, it would bee comfort indeed to have my bones healed, if when they were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, I might then bee at quiet; but alas, what comfort is it now to bee healed of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when Gods chaſtening hand purſues me ſtill, and layes more, and greater troubles up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee continually? for though the trouble of the bones bee the height of trouble; yet it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13931:13"/>is but the trouble of the bodie; my ſoule all this while hath beene at quiet, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>3</label> but now my ſoule it ſelfe is troubled alſo, and ſo extremly troubled, that I feele it, and feele it ſenſibly, in all the parts of my ſoule; I feele it in my memory, when I remember the grievous ſins I have committed: I feele it in my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when I conſider thy glorious Majeſty, whom I have offended: I feele it in my will, when I thinke upon the terrour of thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which I have incurred. If the trouble were but in this or that part onely: I might yet finde comfort in the other: but now that every part of my ſoule, now that all my whole ſoule is troubled, and extremly troubled; Alas, now I may truly ſay, was ever ſorrow, like my ſorrow, was ever trouble like this of mine?</p>
            <p>But can the ſoule bee troubled? is it not a ſpirituall ſubſtance? and are not all earthly things too groſſe, to trouble that which is a ſpirit? They ſhould bee ſo indeed, and they would be ſo indeed, if the ſoule had her right. But alas, while wee live here, the ſoule is but an Inmate to the bodie, and therefore the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy crowes over it, as being upon its own dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, and makes us all of kinne to <hi>Martha,</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about many things, when but one is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And yet theſe be not the things that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the noble ſoule, not the ſoule of <hi>David.</hi> In matters indeed between the World and us, the ſoule is forced to looke downe upon the earth, as upon that which ſuſtaines it, and if it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13931:13"/>finde a want there, it findes withall a trouble indeed; but a trouble to the body onely: or if to the ſoule, but in the bodies behalfe, which is not much: That which properly troubles the ſoule, is the proper trouble of the ſoule, and is onely in matters betweene God and us: and in matters of this nature, it lookes up to heaven, for there indeed is the ſoules freehold: and if that inheritance bee once queſtioned, then the ſoule findes it ſelfe in trouble preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo extremely troubled: that where the trouble of the body, is but the bodie of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, this trouble of the ſoule is, I may ſay, the ſoule of trouble: and is not this inheritance queſtioned, if God fall once to rebuke mee in his anger? For ſeeing the inheritance is but a meere gift proceeding from his favour; how can I expect it, if I be in his diſpleaſure? When I was in my greateſt weakneſſe, yet my bones afforded mee at leaſt ſome ſtrength; and when my bones were troubled, yet my ſoule was able to take care of their curing: but now that my ſoule it ſelfe is troubled: Alas, O God, who is there but thy ſelfe onely, of whom I can hope for any comfort? and therefore, O Lord, How long? How long wilt thou let me lye languiſhing in my weakneſſe? How long wilt thou ſuffer me to ſtruggle with oppreſſion? How long wilt thou ſee the extremity of my miſery, and not relieve mee? Thou indeed inhabiteſt Eternity, and no time to thee is either ſhort, or long: but I alas, am a ſubject
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13931:14"/>of times, and nothing ſo much tyrannizeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me, as this tyrant time; and ſpecially when it joynes with miſery: for then, as a thouſand yeares are with thee but as a day, ſo a day with mee is as a thouſand yeares: Meaſure me not therefore by thy ſtandard of Eternity, but meaſure mee by the ſtandard of time: And then O Lord, How long? How long ſhall thy chaſtening hand lye heavie upon mee? How long wilt thou poure upon mee the vialls of thine indignation? How long ſhall my ſoule bee kept from her true inheritance, which is, to beare a part in the conſort of Angels? My ſoule is a free ſpirit, and is with nothing ſo much delighted, as with liberty; with nothing ſo much vexed, as with thraldome: and in thraldome alas, in miſerable thraldome, is my ſoule detained: and therefore, O Lord, How long? How long ſhall my ſoule bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained of her liberty? How long ſhall I lye groaning in the dungeon of captivity? How long ſhall no date bee ſet, to give a period to my thraldome? My ſoule, I may ſay, is all heart, and therefore every trouble it feeles, muſt needs go to the heart, yet none ſo deepe as this, that I am forced to cry to thee out of the deepe, and cannot yet aſcend out of this vale of miſery: And therefore, O Lord, how long? How long ſhall I live in the death of this feare, the feare of death? How long ſhall I deſire to bee diſſolved, that being reunited againe, I may never more be diſſolved? How
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13931:14"/>long ſhall my immortall ſoule bee kept from the poſſeſſion of her immortality, from the immortality of her poſſeſſion? If the Saints in heaven, who now tread time under their feet, doe yet continue this queſtion ſtill, to ask How long? How long, O Lord, holy, and true, wilt thou not avenge our blood on them that live in the earth; Is it mervaile, that I who live under the tyrannie of time, ſhould beginne this queſtion, to aske how long? How long, O Lord, mercifull, and juſt, wilt thou not avenge me on the world, and ſathan, for the wrongs they have done mee? How long ſhall I bee kept from ſaying, O Death, where is thy ſting, O grave, where is thy victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? How long ſhall the Angell with the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſword, keepe mee from entring againe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Paradiſe?</hi> Where is the morning of joy I promiſed to my ſelfe, when I ſaid, ſorrow may bee in the evening, but joy commeth in the morning? For how many evenings, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tedious nights of ſorrow have I endured, and yet can ſee no morning of joy, no dawning of morning toward? Where is the truth of that Aphoriſme; <hi>Dolor ſi gravis, Brevis,</hi> for what dolour ſo grievous as this of my ſoule, and yet O Lord, how long? How long ſhall I ſtand complaining, and ſay: my ſoule is troubled? Is it not, that I ſhall never ceaſe to ſay, my ſoule is troubled, till he return again, who once ſaid for me, that his ſoule was troubled: For alas, his ſoule ſhould never have beene troubled,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13931:15"/>but to take away, amongſt others, the trouble of mine: ſeeing hee is the ſacrifice for all our ſinnes, and with his ſtripes we are healed. And now therefore, O Lord, how long? How long wilt thou turne away thy face, and not ſhew me again the light of thy countenance? How long wilt thou abſent thy ſelf from me, and not afford me the joy of thy preſence? How long wilt thou bee going ſtill farther from mee, and not ſo much as once offer to returne? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>4</label> Oh returne at laſt and deliver my ſoule, ſave mee for thy mercies ſake; for alas, O Lord, all my troubles are come upon mee, becauſe thou wentſt from mee; all my grievance is long of thine abſence: for as long as thou wert with mee, and that I had thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, my ſoule was at quiet, my bones were at reſt; and I enjoyed then a ſweete and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing calme over all my parts: but as ſoone as thou departedſt from mee, and didſt but turn away thy face; my calme was preſently turned into a tempeſt, a violent tempeſt of thunder and lightening: Thunder of thy rebuking, and lightening of thine anger: that if thou ſtay not thy hand from chaſtening, and return the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, I ſhall never bee able to hold out living, to taſte of thy mercie. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was never ſo neere drowning, when hee cried out to Chriſt, Lord ſave mee, or elſe I periſh: as <hi>David</hi> is now neere ſinking in the pit of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if God returne not ſpeedily, and deliver his ſoule. But what ſpeake I of <hi>David,</hi> as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13931:15"/>though it were not my owne caſe? and if my danger bee as great, ſhall not my prayer be as earneſt? or can I finde a better way of ſaving, then thy returning? No, O Lord; for if thou returne, I am ſure thou wilt not, I know thou canſt not leave thy mercy behind: and mercie when it comes, I know it cannot, I am ſure it will not ever ſuffer it to bee perdition: For though my ſoul were at the pits brink, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to fall in, yet even then would mercie put forth her hand and ſave mee.</p>
            <p>Thou requireſt mee to returne to thee; and alas, O Lord, how can I, if thou returne not to mee firſt? can I come to thee, unleſſe thou draw mee? and canſt thou draw mee to thee, if thou withdraw thy ſelfe from mee? I know thou returneſt continually, to diſpoſe and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Oeconomie of thy creatures: but this returning is in thy providence, and is not that which I deſire: I know thou returneſt often to viſit and judge the ſinnes of the world, as thou didſt at <hi>Sodome:</hi> but this returning is in thy juſtice, and therefore, neither is this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning for my turn; but thou haſt a returning, in Grace and favour, when thou returneſt to mee, to make mee returne to thee, a retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from thine anger to thy patience, from thine indignation to thy loving kindneſſe: and this is the returning which I ſo earneſtly deſire and ſue for.</p>
            <p>But O my ſoule, before God returne in this manner to thee, thou muſt looke to heare him
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13931:16"/>expoſtulate with thee in this manner: Alas my Creature, what haſt thou done, to bring theſe troubles upon thy ſelfe? Did I not make thee at firſt a ſound bodie, and did I not give it a ſtrong conſtitution? and how happens it now that thy bones ſhould bee troubled? Did I not breathe into it a perfect ſoule, and gave it endowments, after mine owne image? and how comes it now to bee ſo quite out of order, and ſo cleane bereft of all my graces? Thou wilt perhaps anſwer; It is true O Lord, my bones are troubled: and how can they chuſe, ſeeing thou tookeſt one of them away from mee, which thou gaveſt mee at firſt? My ſoule alſo is troubled: and how can it chuſe, ſeeing thou didſt ſuffer the Serpent in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> to diſturb and trouble it? But may not God then juſtly reply, I took one of thy bones from thee indeed, but it was to make thee an helper: I let in the Serpent into <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe</hi> indeed, but it was to try thee, for thy bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perfecting; and when I ſaw thee ſo fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurt thy ſelfe with thy helper, and ſo eaſily wonne from mee by a Tempter; had I not juſt cauſe to leave thee to them, for whom thou lefteſt me? and now forlorne wretch, what haſt thou to ſay, unleſſe thou have leave to ſay; Return, O Lord, and deliver my ſoule, ſave mee for thy mercies ſake.</p>
            <p>But what more neceſſity is there of Gods returning to deliver his ſoule, then there was before to heale his bones? and in that caſe he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13931:16"/>ſpake not a word of returning: and why ſhould hee more importune it now? Is it not, that many diſeaſes may be well enough cured, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by relation of ſymptomes, though the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian come not where the patient is: and of this ſort it ſeemes was the healing of his bones: but to deliver his ſoule, is of another nature, and requires perhaps a feeling the pulſe, perhaps, an inſpection of the patient: and therefore no remedie, here but the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt himſelfe bee preſent.</p>
            <p>But is it enough to make ſuite to God in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall terms, to pray him to deliver my ſoule, and not tell from what it is, hee muſt deliver it? Can any man thinke that God will returne up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo uncertaine an occaſion? Alas, O Lord, it is not unknown to thee, that my ſoule wants no clothes: and therefore, it is not to deliver it from nakedneſſe: my ſoule needs no meat, and therefore it is not to deliver it from hunger: my ſoule is never old, and therefore it is not to deliver it from the wrackes of time; but it is indeed to deliver it from trouble: and what it is that can trouble my ſoule, thou knoweſt: for my ſoule is thy ſervant, depending wholy upon thy favour, and having offended thee, deſires to bee delivered from all feare of thine anger: My ſoule was at firſt a free ſpirit, but is now become a bondſlave to ſinne, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſires to bee delivered from this bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: My ſoule is it ſelfe immortall, but is troubled here with a mortall body, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13931:17"/>deſires to bee delivered from this bodie of death: and in effect it is all but ſinne, and the traine that ſinne drawes after it, from which I deſire my ſoule ſhould bee delivered. And therefore returne, O Lord, and deliver my ſoule, ſave mee for thy mercies ſake.</p>
            <p>But O my ſoule, with what reaſon canſt thou expect that God ſhould ever returne to thee? for who would bee willing to come to one in trouble, as thou art, leſt hee pay for his comming, with drawing a trouble upon himſelfe? and if hee ſhould returne and come unto thee, wouldſt thou bee ſo ſatisfied? wouldſt thou not preſently bee importuning him for further favours? Hee muſt helpe thee in thy troubles; He muſt helpe thee out of thy troubles, or thou wouldſt never bee at quiet. And is it a ſmall matter to deliver a ſoule out of trouble? Do ſoules uſe to bee troubled for trifles? and were he not better then to endure thy importunity for his returning, then being returned, to bee troubled with importunitie for thy deliverance? But O my ſoule, be not frighted with theſe vaine objections: for, is God like man, that hee ſhould bee afraid of being troubled? Is he not the God of mercy; and can it bee a trouble to his mercie, to doe the workes of mercie? Is it not his delight to bee; Is it not his title to bee called; Is not his glory to bee counted a deliverer? and is any deliverance ſo fit for his mercie, ſo worthy of his mercie, as deliverance of ſoules? Alas,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13931:17"/>O Lord, it is a ſmall worke for thee to return; but thou ſhalt doe an infinite worke by thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning: for thou ſhalt deliver my ſoule out of trouble, my grieved ſoule out of grievous troubles; and wilt thou not afford me ſo much kindneſſe, to doe ſo ſmall a matter, for effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſo great a matter? Oh returne, O God, and deliver my ſoule, that as thou art called a deliverer, ſo I may call thee my deliverer, and may ſing with <hi>Moſes:</hi> Thou, O God, art my ſtrength, and my ſong, for thou haſt been my deliverance.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould this be made ſo great a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? For though in ſaying, returne, O Lord, and deliver my ſoule: I ſeeme to require of God, two ſeverall workes: one to return, and another to deliver mee; yet they are in truth but both as one: at leaſt, no more differing then the cauſe and the effect; ſeeing his very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning is it ſelfe a deliverance. The onely tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his face towards mee, makes mee to ſee the light of his countenance; and no ſooner doth that light ſhine upon my ſoule, but all the clouds that darkened it, are preſently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled: all the troubles that vexed my bones, are inſtantly healed. But though deliverance bee an effect of Gods returning, yet it muſt bee when hee returnes in a good moode, and not in a rebuking, or in a chaſtening diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for if his anger continue ſtill, were it not better for mee, hee ſhould tarry away? and why then am I ſo importunate with him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13931:18"/>before I know in what termes I ſtand with him; and whether hee bee angry ſtill, or no? but it is even for this that I importune his returning, that I may bee aſſured his anger is paſt; for as long as hee is angry, hee never comes where I am; to doe that, were a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter favour then his anger can afford; but as ſoone as his anger is a little over, hee is apt of himſelfe to returne unto mee; for his delight is with the children of men, and ſpecially with thoſe that call upon him: and when he returns, his anger being over, hee uſeth to doe as the Dove did, that when the waters were a little abated, returned into the Arke, and brought the Olive branch with her in her mouth: ſo God returning, when the waters of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure are a little abated, brings the Olive branch of peace, and deliverance along with him.</p>
            <p>But ſay my ſoule that God ſhould returne, and ſhould deliver thee; wouldſt thou then be quiet, and not trouble him with any more ſuits? ſhould this bee the laſt requeſt thou wouldſt make? Alas no, I have one ſuit more to make; and Thou O God, that gaveſt <hi>Abraham</hi> leave to importune thee with one ſuite after another, vouchſafe mee this favour, to make this ſuite alſo, and this indeed ſhall bee the laſt I will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make: Save mee for thy mercies ſake. For as thy returning would bee to ſmall purpoſe if thou didſt not deliver me: ſo thy deliverance will bee to ſmall purpoſe, if thou doe not alſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13931:18"/>ſave me. To deliver mee, and then leave me to bee ſeized upon againe, would make thee but <hi>Author imperfecti operis;</hi> leave thy worke im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, which cannot agree with the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy moſt perfect workmanſhip. And now, O God, if thou take pleaſure in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, be pleaſed to take pleaſure in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, not to joyne thy rebuking and thy anger together: not to joyne thy chaſtening and thy indignation together, but to joyne thy deliverance and ſalvation together: for thoſe conjunctions ſeperate us from thee, this conjunction unites us to thee: thoſe bring us to ſhipracke, this brings us into the Haven: Deliverance avoids the rocks, ſalvation ſets ſafe on ſhore. And is not this that which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> meanes, when in another place hee ſaith, With thee, O God, there is plenteous redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption? It is redemption indeed, if thou but onely deliver my ſoule: but it is not plenteous redemption, unleſſe beſides delivering, thou alſo ſave mee. O then bee pleaſed in thy plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous redemption, to grant mee this conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of deliverance and ſalvation, that I may returne thee the conjunction of praiſe and thankſgiving; and may ſing and ſay, O Lord, I will praiſe thee: though thou waſt angry with mee, yet thine anger is turned away. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, God is my ſalvation, I will cruſt, and not bee afraid.</p>
            <p>But how can God returne to deliver mee, and to ſave mee: if hee returne not a deliverer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13931:19"/>and a ſaviour? and when will this bee? O my ſoule, in how much better ſtate art thou, then <hi>David</hi> was? for hee onely expected when it ſhould bee, but thou art aſſured when it was. For then was God manifeſted to returne a deliverer, and a Saviour, when the Angell brought this tidings to the ſhepherds; This day is borne to you a Saviour, of whom alſo a voice from heaven teſtified; This is my wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed. Oh then return to me, in this Saviour, in whom, thou art well pleaſed: that ſo I may bee ſure, for ſo I ſhall bee ſure thou wilt not chaſten me in thy diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>As there have beene many particular Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and flouds, yet but one generall: ſo there have beene many particular deliverers and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours, yet but one generall: and from this generall Saviour it is that I deſire &amp; expect ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: for though his being a generall Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, may make him bee thought leſſe carefull of mee, having ſo many others to care for beſides: yet have no feare of that, my ſoule, ſeeing hee is as much a Saviour to mee, as if he were a Saviour to none but mee; and this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Saviour will ſave mee generally, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from temporall, but from ſpirituall enemies: Not onely from trouble of bones, but from trouble of ſoule: Not onely from miſeries here on earth, but even from miſeries, when earth it ſelfe ſhall bee no more. O happy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, when this Saviour ſhall come and ſave
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13931:19"/>mee: but how may I doe to get him to come? for hee comes not but upon ſome motive. If I had all the gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> I would willingly give it all, to get him to come and ſave mee: but, alas, I neither have it to give, nor doth he care to have it: if any thing winne him to doe it, it muſt bee for his mercies ſake, and for his mercies ſake hee will doe it, if ever hee will doe it.</p>
            <p>But is not this ſtrange? My weakneſſe was the motive before to move God to mercy; and muſt his mercie now be it ſelfe the motive to move him to ſave mee? yet ſo it is: For when Gods mercie findes no motive from us; rather then fayle of moving, it becomes a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to it ſelfe: and happy it is from us, that ſo it is: for elſe we might often be without it, when moſt wee need it: or rather alwaies bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, ſeeing wee alwaies need it. Indeed this motive, For his mercies ſake, is the <hi>Primum mobile</hi> of all motives to God, for ſhewing his favour. Hee had never delivered the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but for his mercies ſake: Hee had never ſaved <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke, but for his mercies ſake: but above all, Hee had never ſent his Sonne to ſave the world, but for his mercies ſake: And how then can I doubt, and not rather be confident, that for his mercies ſake hee will alſo deliver my ſoule, and ſave mee. Never therefore my ſoule looke after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further motives: for upon this motive will I ſet up my reſt: His mercie ſhall be both my
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13931:20"/>Anchor, and my harbour; it ſhall bee both my Armour, and my Fortreſſe: it ſhall be both my ranſome and my garland; it ſhall bee both my deliverance and my ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And now, O God, thou ſeeſt the manifold troubles I am in, thou ſeeſt how weake I am; thou ſeeſt how my bones are troubled; thou ſeeſt how my ſoule is troubled; and what now can thy chaſtening hand have more of me, but onely to take away my life? and even my life I would willingly make a ſacrifice to appeaſe thy diſpleaſure. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> But alas, O Lord, what good can it bee to thee, to have mee die? Can I praiſe thee in the duſt? but can I praiſe thee when I am turned to duſt? Is there remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thee in death? or is there hallowing of thy Name in the grave? As long as I have breath in my bodie, I can praiſe thy Name: unworthily indeed, but yet I can praiſe it: As long as I am numbred among the living, I can ſhew my ſelfe thy ſervant; an unprofitable one indeed, but yet a ſervant: but if my ſoule and bodie bee diſſolved once, alas, then all my ſervice of prayſing thee is at an end, I cannot then doe it, though I would; but I cannot then will it, though I ſhould: my ſoule will want her inſtruments with which thy praiſes ſhould be ſounded. O vile death, I hate thee for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much, as for thy hindring mee in this ſervice? O cruell grave, I abhorre thee ſo much for nothing, as for thy ſtopping my mouth for this prayſing? O mercifull God,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13931:20"/>If I could but remember thee in death, I would never bee loath to die. If I could but praiſe thee in the grave, I would willingly goe to it of my ſelfe, and never bee carried to it by force: but alas, death is forgetfull, the grave is dumbe; and therefore deliver my ſoule, O God, ſave mee for thy mercies ſake.</p>
            <p>It is not life that is ſo deare unto mee: but that in life I may praiſe thee, that art ſo deare unto mee: It is not death that is ſo frightfull to mee, but this affrights mee in death, that being dead, I cannot remember thee: It is not the grave that is ſo loathſome to mee, but that in the grave I am forced to forget thee; If death will ſpare me but to praiſe thee, let death come and never ſpare mee: If the grave will but let mee bee ſenſible of thee, the grave ſhall come and bee welcome to me; but alas, death hath no mercie, the grave hath no ſenſe: and therfore return, O Lord, and deliver my ſoule, ſave mee for thy mercies ſake.</p>
            <p>Who knowes not, that death is a mortall enemie to all naturall memory: and therefore makes all men at laſt to end in a Lethargie: and what hope then of remembring thee in death? Who knows not that the grave never opens its mouth to let out any thing, but ſtill to take in? and what meanes then of praiſing thee in the grave. If I could but get death to learne the Art of memory, or if I could but heare the grave to ſay once it had enough; I could then like to have ſome dealing with death, ſome
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13931:21"/>traffique with the grave but alas, deaths Lethargie is incurable, the graves mouth is inſatiable; and therefore returne, O Lord, and deliver my ſoule, ſave mee for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake.</p>
            <p>But doth <hi>Davids</hi> prayer tend to this, that hee may not ſee death? is this the intent of his requeſt, that hee may not deſcend into the pit? doth hee pray to bee as <hi>Enoch,</hi> or <hi>Elias,</hi> taken from the earth, without returning into earth? Alas, hee knowes this to bee either altogether impoſſible, or altogether unlikely: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no likely requeſt to bee made by ſo wiſe a man. This therefore is certainely the intent of his prayer, that God will not ſo chaſten him in his indignation, as to leave him in the hands of death: but that as death receives him from life, and delivers him to the grave, ſo the grave receiving him from death, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him againe to life, that as Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Apoſtles to ſhake off the duſt from their feet, when they came into any unworthy houſe, and to come away; ſo hee comming into this unworthy houſe of death, the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of the grave, may bee able to ſhake off the duſt from his feet, and by the power of of him that ſaid, <hi>Lazarus</hi> come forth, have his ſoule and bodie reunited againe: and ſo u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited, bee admitted into the quire of Saints and Angels, eternally to ſing the eternall Allelujah. For as the departing of the ſoule from the bodie, is the death of the bodie; ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13931:21"/>the dividing of the bodie from the ſoule, is a kinde of death to the ſouler that it is not, as it would bee, nor fully enjoyes it ſelfe, untill it can meete with the bodie, and bee united to it againe: For though it find the bodie here but a baſe cottage, or rather a loathſome priſon, yet it ſhall finde it there a glorious Palace, or rather a holy Temple conſecrated to God: and therefore untill this bee had, it will not fully be accompliſhed that is here prayed for: Returne, O God, and deliver my ſoule, ſave mee, for thy mercies ſake.</p>
            <p>The remembrance of this, that I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memember thee in death, makes mee forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of my ſelfe in life: and becauſe I cannot praiſe thee, nor pray to thee in the grave, it makes me to ſigh and weepe to thee in my bed: and what I want in continuance, to ſupply with violence. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>For I am weary with my ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: all the night make I my bed to ſwimme, I water my cowch with my teares.</hi> Oh let my remembring thee in life, ſupply the place of my forgetting thee in death: and when I lye in my grave ſenſleſſe and ſilent, bee pleaſed to remember how I have lyen in my bed ſighing and weeping. My ſinnes, as being diſordinate paſſions, make me undergo a paſſive pennance: and this hath beene my weakneſſe, my trouble of bones, and my trouble of ſoule: but being alſo diſordinate actions, they make mee liable alſo to doe active pennance: and what is this, but my ſighing, and my weeping? and though
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13931:22"/>I cannot act ſorrow, ſo well as ſinne, yet my bed and my couch can be witneſſes of my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, as well as of my ſinne. Mine eyes indeed chiefly have done the pennance, becauſe mine eyes firſt began the offence: if mine eyes had not ſet mee firſt on fire, mine eyes had not ſhed ſuch ſhowers of teares: but now, how could burning bee quenched but with water? how burning riſing from mine eyes; but with water falling from mine eyes? But yet why ſhould my bed ſuffer? for my bed had no hand in the fault of mine eyes? but alas, how could my bed but prove a <hi>Deodand;</hi> which ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, I may ſay, did <hi>Movere ad mortem?</hi> Though my bed were not principall in the act, yet my bed was acceſſary to the fact, as recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unlawfull and ſtollen pleaſures.</p>
            <p>But though my ſinnes indeed bee my grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemies, yet there are perſonall enemies that have their malignity alſo, which though I cannot ſay they trouble mee as ill, yet I may truely ſay, they trouble mee as well as theſe: for mine eye is conſumed becauſe of griefe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> and is waxen old, becauſe of all mine enemies. You may ſay perhaps that my ſighes were feigned, and that my teares were counterfeit: but the conſumption of mine eye, is a witneſſe of my ſorrow, without exception; that if my paſſive pennance before, were not cauſe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient: at leaſt, my active pennance now gives mee juſt cauſe to ſay, Was ever ſorrow like my ſorrow? was ever griefe like this of mine?
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13931:22"/>And all this pennance I ſuffer and doe, becauſe of mine enemies: for how could I chuſe but ſigh and weepe, to ſee the vile, the execrable dealing of mine enemies, that perſecute me in their hearts, and yet ſpeake peace with their mouthes: that lay ſhares to entrap mee, and yet beare mee in hand it ſhall be for my good: that prejudice my cauſe, as if it would never ſucceed; and prejudicate my prayers, as if they would never bee heard.</p>
            <p>But what meanes <hi>David</hi> by this? will not his weeping make his enemies rejoyce the more? will not the ſeeing him thus dejected, make them the more inſulting over him? will they not bee readie to ſay, Is this hee that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered a Lion, and a Beare? Hee that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred combate with a Giant, the terrour of a whole Armie; and now to fall a crying one cannot tell for what? But <hi>David</hi> is a better husband of his teares then to ſpend them idly, hee knowes for what hee ſpends them, becauſe of his enemies indeed, but not for feare of his enemies: They are neither teares of feare; for whom ſhould hee feare, that hath God on his ſide? Nor teares of vaine glory; for why then ſhould hee ſhed them in the night, when none can ſee them: Nor teares of joy; for how then ſhould they make him looke old, which is an effect of griefe: but they are tears of ſupplication, and teares of compaſſion. Firſt of ſupplication; that God will either convert them, or confound them: and not converting,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13931:23"/>then teares of compaſſion, to thinke of their confuſion. For ſuch is the tenderneſſe of a godly eye, that it hath teares to ſhed even for enemies: And when theſe two waters, the teares of ſupplication, and the teares of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion meet together, what mervaile if they make a floud in <hi>Davids</hi> bed, ſeeing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of like waters made the great Deluge in the whole world? for what are his teares of ſupplication, but as the waters that roſe from the ſprings of the earth? and what are his teares of compaſſion, but as the waters that fell from the Cataracts of heaven? Or is it not perhaps that <hi>David</hi> makes his enemies here, a figure of his ſinnes, which are indeed his greateſt enemies? as alſo that hee makes his owne paſſion, a figure of Chriſts compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which was indeed one of his paſſions? for then hee wept over <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their confuſion, when with teares of ſupplication hee could not prevaile with them, in compaſſing their converſion: when they would not heare him how often hee would have gathered them together as a Hen gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her Chickens, with teares of ſupplication, Then they heare him ſay, There ſhall not a ſtone be left upon another, which ſhall not be caſt down, with teares of compaſſion.</p>
            <p>I grieve not ſo much that mine eye is waxen old, though it bee waxen old with griefe, as I grieve to ſee that my enemies have no eyes at all, at leaſt, no eyes but of malice, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13931:23"/>at my afflictions, and make themſelves as merry with my weeping eyes, as the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims</hi> made themſelves with <hi>Sampſons</hi> blinded eyes. I grieve to ſee their deſtruction draw neere, and they laugh at my grieving, and at the oldneſſe, and alteration which griefe hath brought upon mee. And was it not ſo with my Saviour Chriſt, which made the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſay; thou art not yet fifty yeares old, as though he looked like one neere fifty, when hee was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed not much above thirty:</p>
            <p>But ſeeing with all my ſighing and grieving, I cannot reclaim them; I here diſclaime them: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> 
               <hi>Depart from mee, all ye workers of iniquitie:</hi> Away from mee, all yee that are Wolves in ſheepes cloathing: I put not away poore pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinners, that do pennance for their ſins as I have done, and may rather bee ſaid to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſinne, then to doe it; as being more of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, then of will: I put away them that make iniquitie their work, and thinke it a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance when they bee not committing of ſinne: Them that are journeymen to the trade, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maſters in the myſterie, Them that vilifie my ſighes, and ſay, they are but ſutors <hi>In for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma pauperis,</hi> and therefore that God ſcornes them that reproach my teares, and ſay, they are but dumbe ſolicitors, and therefore God cannot heare them: but ſee how much they are deceived: For now contrary to their hopes, and more to their wiſhes; The Lord hath heard the voice of my teares, hath heard it:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13931:24"/>and therfore does not ſcorn it; the voice of my teares, and therefore my teares are not dumbe: and where all other voices may bee doubted, whether God will heare them or no: the voice of teares, hath Gods eare, I may ſay, at command; at leaſt is never denied acceſſe unto his hearing. And this is but my firſt, and loweſt degree of comfort, for a higher then this: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> Hee hath heard my requeſt. But what? hath God no Maſters of Requeſt about him, but is Maſter of Requeſts himſelfe? Indeed when hee would know the ſinnes of <hi>Sodome,</hi> hee tooke not information from the Angels, but came downe himſelfe to ſee: and ſhould he in perſon ſee ſinnes, and not in perſon heare prayers? And to ſhew himſelfe to be his own Maſter of requeſts indeed, he hath taken my pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition into his hands; that I cannot now doubt of having my requeſt granted: ſeeing the Prince that muſt grant it, is himſelfe the Maſter of Requeſts to preſent it: and what is it to receive a ſupplication into his hands, but to receive the ſuppliant into his favour?</p>
            <p>If hee onely heard the voice of my teares; I might doubt leſt he thought them but like the teares of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſo ſhould ſlight them: Or if hee onely heard my requeſt, I might feare leſt he thought it but like the requeſt of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Zebedees</hi> ſonnes, and ſo reject it: but now that hee hath taken my ſupplication into his hands, now I may bee ſure hee meanes to doe ſomething in it: ſeeing hee never takes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13931:24"/>any thing in hand, which hee brings not to a happy and ſucceſſefull period, againſt all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. The voice of my tears brought God to caſt his eye upon mee: My requeſt brought him to bow his eare unto mee: but the taking my ſupplication into his hand, hath brought him to compaſſionate my eſtate: and ſeeing his compaſſion is active, and his pitty relieving; my teares of ſorrow may now bee turned into teares of joy, my lamentations into ſongs of thanks giving. The lamentable accent of my language, made God firſt to looke upon mee: The pittifull nature of my ſuite, made him next to liſten to mee: but the juſtneſſe of my cauſe in hand, made him laſtly, to take my pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into his hand, which is in effect to grant it out of hand.</p>
            <p>Indeed God is with no muſicke ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, as with that of voyces; with no voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſo much, as with thoſe of teares; with no teares ſo much, as with thoſe of the heart, and ſuch were mine, though ſent forth by the eies: And now, whoſe eyes would not be moved at ſo ſtrange a ſight, to heare eyes ſpeak? whoſe eares would not be moved at ſo ſtrange a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, to ſee tears bee a ſutour? whoſe hands would refuſe ſo ſtrange a writing, where eies, I may ſay, are the Penne, teares the Inke, and ſighes the paper? Pardon my curioſity O God, in imagining wonders, while I meditate of thee, in whom are nothing but wonders.</p>
            <p>And what remaines now, but that my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13931:25"/>remove their lodging, and ſojourn with my enemies, as they have done with me: what remaines, but that my ſighes bee turned upon mine enemies breaſts, my teares upon their eyes, and that the pit they digged for me, they may fall into themſelves; and that, with the violence of falling ſuddenly. As for me, I ſhall live to ſee mine enemies turne their backs and be aſhamed: I ſhall live to ſee them hide their faces, and be confounded: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all, and above all, I ſhall live to magnifie thy glorious Name, O God, who art bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>But is <hi>Davids</hi> charity come to this, to bee turned into curſings and imprecations? Indeed no otherwiſe then God to the Serpent, when hee ſayd, Curſed art thou above all Cattell: for when men are growne into that reprobate ſenſe, that they are more like to limbes of Sathan, then to creatures after the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God; then it is lawfull in Gods cauſe, to take Gods courſe, and to turne them over to ſhame and confuſion. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:13931:25"/>
            <head>THE TWO AND THIRTIETH PSALME.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed is hee whoſe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie is forgiven, and whoſe ſinne is covered.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not iniquitie, and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> When I kept ſilence my bones waxed old, through my roaring all the day long.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> for day and night thy hand was heavie upon mee; my moyſture is turned into the drowth of Summer.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> I acknowledged my ſinne unto thee, and mine iniquitie have I not hid: I ſaid I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13931:26"/>my transgreſsions unto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the iniquitie of my ſinne.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> For this, ſhall every one that is godly pray unto thee in a time when thou maiſt bee found: ſurely the floods of great waters ſhall not come nigh unto him.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Thou art my hiding place; Thou ſhalt preſerve mee from trouble; Thou ſhalt compaſſe mee about with ſongs of deliverance.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> I will inſtruct thee and teach thee in the way which thou ſhalt go: I will fixe mine eye upon thee.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Be ye not as the horſe, or as the mule which have not underſtanding, whoſe mouth muſt be held in with bit and bridle, leſt they come neere unto thee.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Many ſorrowes ſhall bee to the wicked; but hee that truſteth in the Lord, Mercy ſhall compaſſe him about.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Be glad in the Lord, and reioyce ye righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: and ſhout for ioy, all yee that are upright in heart.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:13931:26"/>
            <head>MEDITATIONS and Diſquiſitions upon the 32. Pſalme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſedneſſe was cried in the firſt Pſalme, but was there held ſo deare, that few or none have ever been able to go to the price. Now in this Pſalme it is cried againe, and at a low rate; and if it bee not taken now, it is not like hereafter to bee ever had ſo cheape again. For, where before it muſt have coſt an abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining from ſin, and a perfect delighting in the Law of God, with a continuall exerciſing in it day and night; Now if wee can but get our iniquities to bee remitted, and our ſinnes to bee covered, it will ſerve the turne, and bee accepted.</p>
            <p>But is this ſo much an eaſier rate? For though the purchaſing of Bleſſedneſſe, were before a great worke to bee done, yet it was a worke that might bee done by our ſelves: where the purchaſing it this way, muſt be the worke of another: and were it not better to have it by a way in our owne power, then by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13931:27"/>a way in anothers will? But O my ſoule, Is it in man to direct his own way? Is it in mans power, to performe the worke that is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? hath hee not long ſince put out the light that ſhould have guided him in it? hath hee not long ago cut off the lock, that ſhould have beene his ſtrength to performe it? Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, bleſſed bee hee that affords us bleſſednes at this rate: For though it bee in anothers will to grant it, yet conſider whoſe will it is; even his that is more readie to forgive, then we are readie to aske forgiveneſſe, and is rather a ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour to us to take a pardon, then ſtayes for us to bee ſuitours to have a pardon.</p>
            <p>But may it not bee thought, becauſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe is ſet here at a lower rate, that it is not ſo good a bleſſedneſſe as the other? and then what is gotten by the bargaine? a lower price indeed, but meaner ware. But this cannot bee, for bleſſedneſſe admits no degrees of compariſon; as bleſſed they, that have their ſinnes forgiven, as they (if any ſuch were) that have no ſins to forgive. For though bleſſednes be a poſitive thing, yet it is a ſuperlative thing: and if there want any thing of being a ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, there muſt needs want ſomething of being a bleſſedneſſe. Bleſſed then are they that have their ſins forgiven: for to bee forgiven, is as much as never to have beene guilty: and to ſay, Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven; is all one as to ſay, Bleſſed are they that never ſinned. When our ſinnes are once
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13931:27"/>forgiven, wee are then at peace with God with whom, untill they were forgiven, wee were at enmity: and if no miſery bee compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to this, to have Gods diſpleaſure; then no bleſſedneſſe can be comparable to this, to have his favour: and his favour we ſhall be ſure to have, if he forgive us our ſins; and therefore, Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven.</p>
            <p>But is all the way as ſmooth as this? Is there not a rubbe in the way here? for to ſay, Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven, is very plauſible; but to ſay, Bleſſed are they whoſe ſinnes are covered, ſeemes to marre all. For what if my ſinnes bee ſo great that they cannot bee covered? muſt I therefore be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to loſe my bleſſedneſſe? It is true indeed, though my ſinnes bee in number as the ſands of the Sea, yet the Sea is great enough to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them all: But alas, the ſea covers not ſins, though it cover the ſinners; and what bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can there bee in ſuch a covering? If I goe to the world to cover them, and indeed the world is wide, and no doubt a great cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of ſinnes: but alas, the worlds covering is but Hypocriſie; and what were this, but to cover one ſinne with another, a leſſer with a greater, and ſo I ſhould bee covering them ſtill, and never cover them, but lay them more open in the ſight of God, then they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. If I goe to the Heavens to cover them; and indeed the heavens are large, <hi>Et tegit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Coelum:</hi> but alas, the Heavens are full of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13931:28"/>lights, and will ſooner diſcover that which is hidden, then cover any thing that lies open to view. Yet I may hope to get the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims to cover them, for they have broad wings, and of a wonderfull extent: but alas, the Cherubims have uſe enough of their wings to cover their owne faces: they cannot with all their wings ſo much as cover the leaſt of all my ſinnes. And what hope then to have my ſinnes covered, when neither the Sea, nor the World, neither the Heavens, nor the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims that are above the Heavens, be able to cover them. Yet they muſt bee covered, or there can bee no bleſſedneſſe. And how am I then in any better caſe for attaining of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then I was before? Two waies propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for attaining it, and both impoſſible: There, the price not poſſible to bee payd: Here, the bargaine not poſſible to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. But O Thou that ſitteſt in the Heavens, O Thou that rideſt beteewn the Cherubims, Bleſſed bee thy glorious Name: For thou cameſt thy ſelfe from Heaven of purpoſe to cover them; Thou broughteſt that with thee from Heaven, which onely is able to cover them: for what can cover ſinnes but righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe? what cover infinite ſinnes, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite righteouſneſſe? and where is any infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite righteouſneſſe to bee found, but in him onely that is infiniteneſſe it ſelfe? Be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therefore my ſoule; for now it is not a hope, it is an aſſurance that my ſinnes at laſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13931:28"/>ſhall come to bee covered; It is not a hope, it is an aſſurance, that I ſhall come at laſt to this bleſſedneſſe in covert.</p>
            <p>There are ſome perhaps will grant, that bleſſedneſſe may conſiſt in covering indeed, but not in covering of ſinnes: They thinke rather in covering their Tables with rich plate, and dainty diſhes: or in covering their houſes with ſlates of Gold; like <hi>Aurea domus Neronis;</hi> or in covering their backes with ſilke and ſoft raiment, ſuch as Chriſt ſaith are in Kings hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: but <hi>Nabuchodonozor</hi> will come in for one, <hi>Dives</hi> for another, and <hi>Haman</hi> for a third, and give cleer evidence that all theſe are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and that <hi>David</hi> onely tells us the truth; They, they onely are the bleſſed men whoſe ſinnes are covered.</p>
            <p>But what needs all this ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning and diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? For, what more myſterie is there in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and whoſe ſinnes are covered; then if it were ſaid, Bleſſed are they, from whoſe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities thou turneſt away thy face, and whoſe offences thou blotteſt out? Or, (becauſe the Scripture hath plenty of expreſſings in this kinde) then if it were ſayd; Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities thou caſteſt behind thy back, and whoſe ſinnes thou removeſt from thee as farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt? for to what tends this variety of expreſſing, but either for illuſtration: or at moſt, for vehemencie of aſſeveration, that our ſinnes are pardoned?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13931:29"/>But if it be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceived to be not ſo much a divers expreſſing of the ſame way, as an expreſſing of a divers way to bleſſedneſſe; then indeed, as being more myſticall, it will bee more miſty for diſcerning cleerly what the meaning of <hi>David</hi> is. Is it then, that forgiving our ſinnes is the worke of Gods mercie; for it is mercies worke onely to forgive; covering our ſinnes, the worke of his love; for love covers the multitude of ſinnes: not imputing our ſinnes, the worke of his will; as hee ſaith, I will have mercie, on whom I will have mercie: that ſo wee may have here a three fold cord of Gods goodneſſe to relye upon for our bleſſedneſſe? Or is it, that remiſſion is neceſſary for ſins of commiſſion, Covering, neceſſary for ſins of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; but not imputing may ſerve for ſins of tranſmiſſion; that is, for ſin originall, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us from our firſt Parents? Or is it that forgiving is mentioned as the worke of God the Father, whoſe worke properly it is to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give: as hee ſaith, I am he that blot out tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions: Covering is mentioned as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per work of God the Son; as with whoſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe our ſins are covered: and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Put yee on the Lord Chriſt Ieſus: Not imputing is mentioned as the work of the holy Ghoſt; who being all love, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionates our infirmities, and ſo all the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Deitie have a hand, (as it is fit they ſhould) in this great worke of procuring to us our bleſſedneſſe: that as at the making of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13931:29"/>man at firſt; ſo at the making of man bleſſed at laſt, they may all joyne together, and ſay, <hi>Faciamus hominem ad imaginem noſtram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As long as iniquities are unforgiven, the conſcience lies as it were on a Racke tortured and tormented, day and night; but as ſoone as there comes a pardon, it is preſently taken off the Racke, and layd at eaſe: and is not this a bleſſedneſſe? As long as our ſinnes remaine uncovered, God turnes away his face, and frownes upon us; but as ſoone as our ſinnes bee covered, hee ſhewes us againe the light of his countenance: and is not this a bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? As long as our ſinnes are imputed to us, wee are in the ſtate of <hi>Adam</hi> when hee was caſt out of Paradiſe: but as ſoone as wee are freed from this imputation, we preſently heare Chriſt ſay; This day thou ſhalt bee with mee in Paradiſe: and is not this again a bleſſedneſſe? And is it not now, that <hi>David</hi> expreſſeth it three waies, to ſhew, that by it a godly man is not onely bleſſed, but thrice bleſſed?</p>
            <p>But ſeeing forgiving, and covering, and not imputing of ſinnes, are all but privative things; how can they make a bleſſedneſſe, which is a poſitive thing? They may take away miſery, but can never make a bleſſedneſſe. But is not the very taking away of miſery, in this caſe, a bleſſedneſſe? for ſeeing we were ordained by God at firſt, to a bleſſed eſtate, and nothing barres us from that eſtate, but ſinne; are wee not by the removing this barre, either left in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13931:30"/>this eſtate, or at leaſt reſtored to it againe? O gracious God, grant mee the forgiveneſſe of mine iniquities, and the covering of my ſins, and let mee never come at Heaven, if I make not of theſe privatives, a <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder to climbe up to Heaven. Neither yet is remiſſion of ſinnes a meere privative, but it hath in it an influence of Grace alſo; which brings with it a ſhowre of bleſſings, turnes <hi>Ebal</hi> into <hi>Geri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zim:</hi> and of the Theefe upon the Croſſe, makes a ſaint in Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>Hitherto, <hi>Davids</hi> doctrine wee may well ſubſcribe to, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> but what meanes hee by this; <hi>And in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile?</hi> For, if there bee no guile in his ſpirit, what needs ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther covering, or forgiving? But is it not, as Chriſt ſayd of <hi>Nathaniel:</hi> Behold a true Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite, in whom there is no guile: and yet who doubts, but in <hi>Nathaniel</hi> there was ſinne? It ſeemes therefore meant, that though cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and forgiving bee all Gods worke, yet there is a condition required in him whoſe ſins are to bee forgiven: and this is the condition, that there bee no guile in his ſpirit: but that his repentance bee ſincere and unfeigned, and without hypocriſie. And it is, as if hee had ſayd; Bleſſed is he whom God juſtifies, and juſtifying ſanctifies: for having ſayd, Bleſſed is hee to whom the Lord imputeth no finne; which is our juſtification: it preſently follows, and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile, which is our ſanctification. Or is it here annexed with
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13931:30"/>a conjunction, perhaps to ſhew that ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth not ſo much follow, as it is annexed; and from the ſame breath of Gods ſpirit, riſeth together with juſtification? Or is it therefore added, leſt wee ſhould thinke bleſſedneſſe to be in ſuch ſort Gods gift, as that there ſhould bee nothing required in us towards the attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it: which yet is ſo in us, that it is not of us, but muſt come from God to us? for alas elſe, what ſpirit of ours could be without guile, if it were not influenced by that ſpirit, which is the truth it ſelfe?</p>
            <p>It ſeemes this is a doctrine, in favour plainly of plaine dealing: but is this a world for plain dealing to thrive in? and if no thriving, what bleſſedneſſe? But is it not ſayd of <hi>Iacob,</hi> that hee was a plaine man, and yet would any man deſire to thrive better then he did? who went over <hi>Iordan</hi> with nothing but his ſtaffe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned backe with multitudes of Cattell. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver therefore feare thriving by plaine dealing; for God that requires plaineſſe in thy dealing with him, wil no doubt bleſſe it in thy dealing with others; and they that make themſelves rich by guile, will but finde themſelves begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the end, when God blowes upon them, and that they finde that guile in their fortunes, which they ſo greedily entertained in their ſpirits.</p>
            <p>But why am I ſo earneſt againſt guile in the ſpirit? do I not herein ſpeak againſt my ſelfe? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>3</label> For was there not guile in my ſpirit, when I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13931:31"/>held my peace, for confeſſing my ſinnes, and yet cried out for ſenſe of my paine; as though I would have made God believe, it was for ſenſe of my ſinne? but God knowes I was ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in that, and that ſilence is now cauſe of my roaring: for if I had ſpoken and confeſſed my ſinne at firſt, I might have beene heard in a lower voice: but having deferred my repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſo long, what mervaile if God bee gone ſo farre out of hearing, that a lower voice then roaring will never bee heard? Every ſinne we commit, makes God to turne away his face and depart from us: and the longer time the ſinne is unrepented, the longer time hee hath to goe from us the farther; and the ſlower we are in repenting, the more he haſtens his pace: and have wee not need then to cry the lowder, to make him to heare us, that by long defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our repentance is gone ſo far from us? Oh the fooliſhneſſe of men that deferre repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance! for to deferre the repenting of ſinnes, is a greater ſinne, then the ſinnes to bee repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and have wee not need then of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der voice to obtaine forgiveneſſe, when to our former ſinnes to bee repented, is added this great ſinne of deferring our repentance? O fooliſh tongue, how often haſt thou ſpoken when it nothing concerned thee! and wouldſt thou not ſpeak now when it concerned thee ſo much? how often haſt thou ſpoken at the ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of impatience, and wouldſt thou not ſpeak now at the entreaty of repentance? But why
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13931:31"/>then is it ſayd, <hi>Non ulli tacuiſſe nocet,</hi> as if to hold ones peace did never hurt any? ſilence inded never hurts any by ſins of commiſſion, but by ſinnes of omiſſion often: ſilence is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver guilty of idle words, yet guilty often of idleneſſe, in letting ſlippe opportunity. And therefore <hi>Solomons</hi> counſell ſeemes much the ſounder: There is a time to ſpeake, and a time to hold ones peace: and if there bee a time for each of them, then each of them in their due time is good; out of time is bad: it is as great a fault to bee ſilent when it is fit to ſpeake, as it is to ſpeake when it is fit to bee ſilent: and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time be fit for ſpeaking, unfit for ſilence, this is the time, when ſinnes are to bee confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and when our iniquities are to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and made known to God. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am I juſtly puniſhed for my ſilence: for ſeeing I held my peace when it was fit to ſpeak, now my ſpeaking will not ſerve, but I am faine to roare: ſeeing I would not ſpend a few hours in prayer at firſt, now I am faine to lie crying and praying all the day long. Alas, to what a miſerable ſtate had I brought my ſelfe, that could neither make uſe of my ſilence, nor of my crying out: for if I held my peace, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed my ſin, and the ſore ſtill feſtered more and more: and if I cried out, it ſpent my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and the very paine did Ages worke for it in my bones, and made them old, while my body was young. The truth is, I felt my ſelfe in paine, but knew not what I ayled: I knew
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13931:32"/>all was not well with mee, but knew not well why it was ſo: Now after much ſearching and examining the cauſe, I finde what it was: It was even ſinne, that lay all this while in my boſome, as a fire raked up in the embers of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and burnt mee to the very bone: but finding it to be ſin, I was aſhamed to confeſſeit: and ſo between ſhame of revealing, and danger of not revealing, I lived a long time as a man diſtracted, holding my peace for very ſhame, and crying out for very paine: And alas, O Lord, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>4</label> how could I chuſe, when <hi>it was thy hand that lay heavie upon mee;</hi> thy hand of which it is ſayd, that with it thou doſt terrible things: and that which is in terrour the moſt terrible, when thou once beginneſt, thou never giveſt over: thine anger is not as an Ague, but as a Feaver; comes not by fits, but is a continuall fit without either remiſſion, or intermiſſion: and what mervaile then, if in this torrid Zone of affliction, my Almond tree flouriſh before the time, and my ſtrong men bow themſelves under the burden? As a flower that is parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſunne, and is ready to fall from the ſtalke that upheld it: and as earth that is overdried with the heat, and is ready to crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into duſt and powder: ſuch, O Lord, was I, while neither wind, nor ſo much as a breath of thy favour blew upon mee; while neither ſhowre, nor ſo much as the dew of thy Grace inſtilled into me: and in this maze of diſtreſſe whither could I thinke to turne my ſelfe for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13931:32"/>helpe? I thought ſometimes that time might helpe mee: but alas, time was no friend of mine; for the longer time I ſtayed, the more my ſore feſtered and rankled within mee: then I thought that place might helpe mee; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, I turned mee from ſide to ſide, and could neither finde reſt in reſting, nor eaſe in motion: Then It hought of friends, but alas, my friends were my fortunes, and not mine; they bore mee fayre in hand, while the weather was fair; but as ſoone as a ſtorme came, they ſhrunke in the wetting. So I bethought mee at laſt of a way, which the world would rather thinke a Precipice, then away, and yet perplexed as I was, I thought beſt to venture it. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>I ſaid I will confeſſe my ſinnes to God:</hi> A dangerous way I vow, to goe for helpe to him whom I had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended: to looke, his hand ſhould raiſe me up, that had caſt mee downe: yet ſee the event, or rather wonder at the wonderfulneſſe of Gods goodneſſe; <hi>I confeſſed my ſinne to God: and hee for gave me the iniquitie of my ſinne.</hi> Oh let every ſinfull ſoule take this from mee: There is no ſuch way in the torment of ſin, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it to God. For it is not with God as it is with men, Gods waies are not as mens waies: if wee confeſſe a debt to men, no way but we muſt pay it: but in a debt to God, the very confeſſing it is a payment, and it is inſtead of ability, that we acknowledge our felves to bee unable.</p>
            <p>And indeed, O my ſoule, what danger can
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13931:33"/>there bee in confeſſing thy ſinnes to God, who knowes them alreadie better then thy ſelfe? Thou informeſt him of nothing hee knew not before: thou doſt but diſcharge thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and proſtrate thy ſelfe at the foot of his mercy: and hee is the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah:</hi> and who knowes not that it is the noble nature of the Lion to ſpare any thing that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates it ſelfe before him. If <hi>Adam</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed his ſinne to God, would God have caſt him out of Paradiſe? If <hi>Eve</hi> had confeſſed her ſinne to God, ſhould ſhee have had ſuch throwes in her child-bearing? Oh then let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Adam that would recover Paradiſe, let every <hi>Eve,</hi> that would have eaſe in her labour, confeſſe their ſinnes to God: for they may be confident a true confeſſion ſhall never returne, either unregarded, or unrewarded: that where it was ſaid before, Bleſſed are they whoſe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are forgiven, and whoſe ſinnes are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: wee may now alter the ſtile and ſay, Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and whoſe ſinnes are diſcovered. For if we confeſſe them, God is juſt, and will forgive them; if wee diſcover them, God is mercifull and will cover them: that as it was ſayd of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> he believed, and it was counted to him for rightcouſneſſe: ſo it ſhall bee ſayd of us; wee confeſſe our iniquities, and it is imputed to us for innocencie.</p>
            <p>But is there nothing required to forgivenes of ſins but onely the confeſſing of them? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13931:33"/>confeſſion is but a part of repentance Gods pardons are alwaies entire, and is it likely that he will grant a whole pardon, for onely a piece of repentance? Indeed ſo great is Gods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe in ſhewing of mercy, ſo great his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour towards penitent ſinners: that as he uſeth the figure, I may ſay of Anticipation in his grace to them, ſo he accepts of the figure ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>echdoche in their performance to him: though confeſſion be but a part of repentance, yet if it bee a true part hee accepts it for the whole, and puts a penitent in poſſeſſion of a ful pardon upon his firſt payment. But then it muſt not bee a bare confeſſion, ſuch as the earth was in the beginning, <hi>Vacuaet informis:</hi> of which, it was not ſayd, <hi>Et vidit Deue quod erat bonum:</hi> as the confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudas</hi> was: but it muſt bee <hi>Confeſſio informata,</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of one in whoſe ſpirit is no guile: a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion not onely <hi>Gravida,</hi> but <hi>Parturiens,</hi> In labour, which is contrition: ſuch as the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans was, who in confeſſing ſtroke his breſt. And yet this is not all, but it muſt bee a confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made to God: <hi>Pharaoh</hi> indeed confeſſed, but it was but to <hi>Moſes:</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed, but it was but to the Rulers, neither of them to God, as <hi>David</hi> doth here: and yet, neither is this all, but it muſt bee a confeſſion, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing to confeſſe; as it is here: <hi>I ſayd I will confeſſe my ſinne to God:</hi> and this kinde of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is ſo acceptable to God, that next to a Martyr, hee loves a Confeſſor.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:13931:34"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>For this, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> ſhall every one that is godly pray unto thee in a time when thon maiſt bee found:</hi> for what favour can a prayer looke to finde, that is made to one that is not to bee found? But are there then criticall times for finding of God, as there are for taking of Phyſick, or for ſetting of figures in Aſtrologie? Is not God every where, and therefore to bee found in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place? Eternall, and may be found at any time? O my ſoule, it is neither time nor place that is any conſiderable circumſtance for find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God: but if thou wouldſt know the true place to finde him indeed, thou muſt look him in thy heart: if the trueſt time, thou muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thy repentance: for in a penitent heart are all the conſiderable circumſtances for finding of God, either for time or place: look him there, and then thou ſhalt finde him: look him then, and there thou ſhalt finde him. O then my ſoule, if my heart bee the true place for finding of God, had I not need to looke him there betimes? for how long am I ſure I ſhall keep my heart? I may be ſure, not long; ſeeing it is alwaies upon going, and makes all the haſte it can to be gone: and if it ſhould be gone before I finde God in it, alas my ſoule, there would bee no finding him there, for thee for ever. And as the heart is the true place; ſo what may wee ſay is the true time when God may bee found? What, no doubt, but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time? for ſeeing in God, there is neither time paſt, nor time to come, how ſhould wee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13931:34"/>looke to finde him where hee is not? For this therefore ſhall every one that is godly pray to God while hee may bee found, that is, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and at this very inſtant, and not defer repentance to the time to come, in which God is not found, no more then it is found in God.</p>
            <p>God no doubt may bee found at all times; but wee are not at all times in caſe to finde him: for how ſhould wee finde him, when we have no eyes to looke him? and am I ſure I ſhall have eyes alwaies? God knowes, I am ſure I ſhall not, for I finde them to grow dimmer every day then other; and this dimneſſe ere long, muſt needs end in darkneſſe. Oh then my ſoule, make haſte to finde God, before the cryſtall of thine eyes bee broken: for if thou tarry till then, there will bee no finding him; and if not finde him, no asking him forgivenes: and if not aske it, not have it; and not having forgiveneſſe, there will bee no bleſſedneſſe. For this ſhall every one that is godly pray to God while hee may bee found, that is, before his lights bee put out, and before hee goe to dwell at the City of Wormes, in the dungeon of darknes. There is indeed no finding of God, without repentance, and no repentance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith: which becauſe it ſhall ceaſe in the life to come, we muſt therfore find him now, or ſhall not at all, either here or not hereafter.</p>
            <p>But if no more but repentance bee required for finding of God: what hinders, but he may bee found at any time: ſeeing what hinders,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13931:35"/>but I may repent at any time? O my ſoule, who tells thee ſo? For haſt thou the heart to breake thy heart at any time? and if thou haſt not, then canſt thou not repent at any time: for true repentance is a breaking of the heart. Thou maiſt perhaps quench the ſpirit when thou pleaſeſt: but canſt thou ſet it a burning when thou pleaſeſt? If thou canſt not, then canſt thou not repent when thou pleaſeſt; for a true repentance, is never without a burning ardour of Gods Spirit.</p>
            <p>But is there indeed any time when God may not be found? Is he like to ſome Princes, who ſhut themſelves up in ſtate at times, and are not then to bee ſpoken withall, or ſeene? O great God, thou art not like man, and therefore not found after their manner: found, when onely their perſons are found: but to finde thee, is to find thee gracious, without which, as good loſt thou wert, as found: and gracious can none finde thee, but onely the penitent: and therefore for this, ſhall every one that is godly pray unto thee, ſo that through the grace of a true repentance, hee may finde thee gracious.</p>
            <p>When a ſinne is committed, a ſhower of Gods anger raines preſently downe upon the ſinner; and continues raining, till there be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: and if the repentance bee deferred long, it may raine downe anger ſo long, till it make a floud, and then there will bee no go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere to God for water: but rather the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will goe neere to bee a cauſe of drowning:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13931:35"/>for it is not every ones cafe to have an Arke to ſave himſelfe in from the floud of Gods anger; hee onely may bee confident to bee ſaved, that like <hi>Noah,</hi> begins to make his Arke betimes, and returns to God with a ſpeedy repentance.</p>
            <p>But why is it ſayd, every one that is godly, and not rather, every one that is wiſe? ſeeing it is wiſedome, and not godlineſſe, that can diſcerne the fitneſſe of times and ſeaſons? Is it not, that wiſedome, and godlineſſe in ſpirituall matters, are terms convertible: No true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome without godlineſſe, no godlineſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out true wiſedome: but therefore rather ſaid godly then wiſe, becauſe indeed there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godlineſſe, though there bee other wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>And now, O my ſoule, conſider the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe of a true repentance, and what a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion it makes in a penitent heart: I could never thinke before, but that the world was the ſafeſt ſanctuary; the fleſh, the beſt Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe: but now I canſay; <hi>Thou, O God, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> art my refuge from tribulation;</hi> thou my Iubilee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all perfecutions: the place from which I hid my ſelfe before, is now become the place to hide mee in: and that which I fled from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as my onely terrour, I now flye to as my onely ſuccour. Before I repented, I thought that to go to God, was to runne upon a rocke: but now I finde it is to go into the Haven: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I thought ſtill upon that ſaying, A man ſhall leave Father, and mother, and cleave to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13931:36"/>his wife: but now I finde, that <hi>Adhaerere Deo bonum eſt,</hi> there is no bleſſedneſſe but in clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to God. Before I repented, I aſpired to nothing, but to ſit at <hi>Dives</hi> his table, and to fare deliciouſly every day: I tooke pleaſure in nothing, but in wearing ſoft rayment, in mirth and jollity: but now I finde that all the diſhes I fed on there were poyſon: I find there is no wearing like to ſack-cloth, noſweet pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der like to aſhes, and ſay to laughter thou art mad. Thou, O Chriſt, art the true food that nouriſheth to eternall life: Thou, the true gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that gives mee entrance to the marriage of the Lambe, and makeſt mee to heare the melody of Heaven, in the quire of Angels. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I repented, I ſaid to the world <hi>Aegypt,</hi> thou art my ſtaffe, and to the fleſh <hi>Dalilah,</hi> thou art my joy: but now I can ſay, Thou, O God, art my refuge in all tribulations; Thou, the joy of my heart, againſt all my perſecutors.</p>
            <p>But O the vanity of the world, have I lived to heare that glorious acclamation, <hi>Saul</hi> hath killed his thouſand, and <hi>David</hi> his ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand: and is my glory come now to this, that I am glad of a place to hide me in? Indeed, <hi>Sic tranſit gloria Mundi.</hi> But O my bodie, never doe thou trouble thy ſelfe for the matter, for thou art ſure enough of a place to hide thee, ſeeing a ſpanne or two of earth will ſerve thy turne: It is thou my ſoule, that makeſt mee glad of a place to hide me, for thou indeed art not eaſily hidden, thou ly eſt open to all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13931:36"/>of Sathan, to all temptations of the world, and that which is more then theſe, to the angry hand of God: and from this it is chiefly, I am glad of a place to hide me: though the world may thinke it ſtrange I ſhould goe to God, to hide mee from God: But O fooliſh world, it is not ſtrange, for I goe to Gods Mercy, to hide me from his Iuſtice; for God forbid, I ſhould bee of thoſe, that call to the Mountaines to cover them, and to the Hills to hide them. No, deare Ieſus, Thou art the Mountaine that muſt cover mee; Thou, the Sanctuary, that I flye unto: to which if <hi>Ioab</hi> had fled, it had not been <hi>Abner</hi> that could have drawne him forth.</p>
            <p>But had not <hi>David</hi> Towers, and Fortreſſes to defend him, and could hee not bee ſafe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he were hidden? and ſay he were brought to a neceſſity of hiding himſelfe; yet is hee well adviſed to make choyce of God, for his place to hide him? The darkeſt places are fitteſt for hiding; and what hiding then could he look for of God, who is nothing but light? O my ſoule, there is no hiding ſo excellent, as to be hidden with light; for thither my enemies, who are children of darkneſſe can never come. When I am hidden with light, I can ſee my enemies, and they not ſee mee: not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the advantage that God himſelfe hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us. When I am hidden with light, there is more glory in the light, then deſparagement in the hiding: and have I not reaſon then, to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13931:37"/>make choyce of God who dwells in light inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible, for my place to hide me? Others hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding can but keep me from the eyes of my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, it cannot keepe me from the hands of my enemies: Gods hiding can doe both: For, <hi>Thou, O God, ſhalt preſerve mee from trouble:</hi> though in others hiding, enemies perhaps can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, yet troubles at leaſt may finde mee out; but when thou hideſt mee; as enemies cannot, ſo troubles dare not: I ſhall bee as free from the feare, as from the ſenſe of troubles. And yet, O God, if thou ſhouldſt onely preſerve mee from trouble, this were no more, then I might enjoy, if I were a ſenſleſſe creature; for what trouble, where there is no ſenſe? but thy hiding will do more then this: it will compaſſe me about with ſongs of deliverance: and this wil give me a ſenſe, and in that ſenſe a delight of the happines I enjoy by the benefit of thy hiding.</p>
            <p>If thou ſhouldſt deliver mee but in part, I ſhould in part bee in bondage ſtill: and what would my ſtate bee the better for this? ſeeing in this caſe, all figures are ſynechdoches; a part here as much as the whole: to bee a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in part, is to bee a Priſoner altogether: but when thou compaſſeſt mee about with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; this leaves no place for ſynechdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but gives mee a totall and abſolute free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and makes mee obnoxious to no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation, And yet if thou ſhouldſt alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe mee with deliverance, and ſo leave mee; I might be ſtill both inſenſible of it in my ſelfe,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13931:37"/>and unthankfull for it to thee, and ſo my ſtate but little the better for this neither: but when thou compaſſeſt mee about with ſongs of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; this makes mee a Quiriſter in the Quire (I might ſay of Angells,) but that their ſongs are all ſongs of Iubilee, and mine onely of deliverance. O my ſoule, God is not a deliverer like a halfe Moone, bright in one part, and darke in another; but he is a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer like the Sunne, his deliverance ſhines al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the whole compaſſe: and with his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, hee delivers alſo ſongs of thankfulnes to him, and in my ſelfe of joyfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>But what need is there of Plurality of ſongs? may not one ſong ſerve? and if one may, what need many? One ſong perhaps, may ſerve for one deliverance: but if there bee many deliverances, muſt there not bee many ſongs? and muſt there not be many deliverances, when there are many bondages? and are there not many bondages when I incurre a new bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, as often as I commit a new ſinne? and yet another reaſon as great as this: For ſay that Gods deliverance bee but one, will that one deliverance require but one ſong? O my ſoule, it deſerves, and therefore requires, I ſay not a Pluralitie, but an infinitie of ſongs: for there muſt be ſome ſongs to expreſſe it, and others to extoll it; ſome ſongs of <hi>miſerere,</hi> and others of <hi>Magnificat:</hi> ſome <hi>de profundis,</hi> and others <hi>in excelſis,</hi> ſome ſongs of praiſe, and others of thankſgiving: and though there
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13931:38"/>will bee a time when all theſe ſongs ſhall bee collected into one, and ſo collected make the great <hi>Canticum Canticorum:</hi> yet till that time come, there will bee need of many ſongs: and ſeeing I ſhall need many; I hope, O God, thou wilt not ſee mee want, and tye me to one ſong: but wilt compaſſe mee about with ſongs of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</p>
            <p>But alas, O Lord, I am farre as yet from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compaſſed with ſongs of deliverance; I have not ſo much as one ſong of deliverance to ſing: for how ſhould I ſing of deliverance, that am ſtill in bondage? how ſing at all, that am ſtill a weeping? But I know thy goodnes O God, I know how much thou delighteſt in the Muſicke of Thankſgiving; and therefore, am aſſured, the time will come, and (conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the haſte thou makeſt) will come ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that thou wilt compaſſe mee about with ſongs of deliverance.</p>
            <p>But have I beene all this while right, in the underſtanding of <hi>Davids</hi> meaning, where hee ſaith, Thou ſhalt compaſſe mee about with ſongs of deliverance? for are they ſongs that are ſung for mee, or ſongs that are ſung by mee? if ſung for mee, then they are men and Angells that ſing them, as rejoycing for my deliverance; if ſung by mee, then it is I, O God, that ſing them to thee, as giving thanks for my deliverance. Songs of deliverance, of my deliverance, that I am delivered: or ſongs of deliverance, of thy deliverance, that thou haſt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13931:38"/>delivered me. Take them in either ſenſe, &amp; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> is pleaſ'd; take them either way, and God is glorified. So there need be no queſtion of this, yet of this, there will be queſtion: how I can be ſure of repenting, if I am not ſure to repent whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I liſt? and this queſtion <hi>David</hi> ſeemes to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, putting the matter upon God; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore brings God in, as ſpeaking thus: <hi>I will give thee underſtanding, and will inſtruct thee in the way that thou ſhalt walke; I will fixe mine eye upon thee:</hi> and Gods inſtructions are never in vaine: for with the leſſons hee gives, hee gives alſo an aptneſſe to underſtand them; and with the aptneſſe, a capacity to performe them: and then having God, for an inſtructour, by teaching thee the way, and for an overſeer, by fixing his eye upon thee: how canſt thoudoubt of profiting in a learning, where all the learning is but one leſſon of repentance. Repentance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is but one leſſon: but it is the hardeſt leſſon in all the booke: and wee may ſee how hard it is, by the great adoe that is about it: for firſt, God muſt give us underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for it; and this will not bee enough; then hee muſt give us inſtructions in it; and neither will this bee enough; then hee muſt have a continuall eye upon us, to hold us to it, and all theſe together will be but little enough; Alas, all theſe together will bee too little, and not enough, if wee bee wanting to our ſelves. Bee not therefore, O my ſoule, like the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of which God ſayd, what could I doe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13931:39"/>more to my Vineyard, then I did, and yet it hath brought forth nothing but wilde grapes? No my ſoule, <hi>Bee not like to Horſe and Mule, that have no underſtanding:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> when thou art ſhewed the right way, doe not wilfully runne another way: when one comes to dreſſe and keem be thee, doe not offer to byte and ſtrike; do not caſt thy Riders, nor kicke at thy Rulers: Bee not headſtrong like the Horſe, nor lazy like the Mule: for if thou uſe thy ſelfe like a Horſe and a Mule, thou muſt looke to bee uſed like a Horſe and a Mule; have a bridle put in thy mouth, and a ſnaffle in thy jawes: and if theſe will not ſerve, a ſpurre and a rod too, to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and beate underſtanding into thee. For conſider, O my ſoule, in what ſtate thou ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt: though thou have underſtanding, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made <hi>Ad ſimilitudinem Dei;</hi> yet if thou uſe not underſtanding, thou makeſt thy ſelfe <hi>Ad ſimilitudinem Bruti:</hi> or rather ſo much worſe then a Beaſt, as corruption makes worſe than privation: for if a man ſhall doe that by abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Reaſon, which a Horſe doth by wanting Reaſon; ſhall hee not doe it, not onely with more ſhame, but with more violence, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that an inſtrument of ſtubbornnes, which was given for a furtherance of obedience? Is it not a ſhamefull thing that a man ſhould bee bridled and ſpurred as a Horſe? yet if he uſe not underſtanding, but will bee like a Horſe, hee muſt bee ſo: for as underſtanding is the ſterne, I may ſay, of a man, to direct him in his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13931:39"/>courſe, ſo a bridle is the ſterne of a Horſe to guide him in his way; and he that will not take into his heart, his owne ſterne of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, muſt be forced to take into his mouth, the Horſes ſterne of a bridle; for a ſterne hee muſt have, no remedy, either his owne ſterne or a Horſes, either underſtanding or a bridle: that wee may truely ſay, there is not a more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary trade in the world then a bridle-maker is; ſeeing without ſuch a one, there would bee no living in the world, for the multitude of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulie Horſes.</p>
            <p>And thus when men grow ſo wicked and ſo voyd of underſtanding, to bee like Horſe and Mule: It may juſtly then bee ſayd, <hi>Many are the troubles of the wicked:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>10</label> for there will bee troubles of bridle, and troubles of ſnaffle, troubles of ſpurro, and troubles of rod; from all which the godly are free: No bridle in their mouthes, becauſe they doe that willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which the fooliſh Horſe will not doe but by conſtraint. No ſpurre in their ſides; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with the aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Gods grace, they uſe underſtanding, and run readily of themſelves, to the marke that is before them.</p>
            <p>But why then ſhould <hi>David</hi> in another place ſay; <hi>Many are the troubles of the Righteous?</hi> for by this it ſhould ſeeme, there is nothing loſt by being wicked, nothing gotten by being righteous; for whither wicked or righteous, there will bee troubles ſtill. It is true, there will bee troubles, but is there not a difference?
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13931:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:13931:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:13931:41"/>The troubles of the godly are but onely out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but the troubles of the wicked are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward rather: The troubles of the godly are but to exerciſe them, but the troubles of the wicked tend to ruine. The troubles of the wicked have a Corroſive, I may ſay, a worme within them, but the troubles of the godly have a Cordiall, I may ſay a kernell within them, a ſweet kernell indeed, that makes am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple amends for all the hardneſſe and fracture of their ſhell. The troubles of the wicked, have no deliverer: but of the troubles of the godly, it is ſayd, <hi>The Lord ſhall deliver them out of all.</hi> And all this long <hi>of Gods mercy</hi> that compaſſeth them about. It is no doubt, a ſtrong fortreſſe to the godly, that the Angells pitch their tents about them: but it is a far ſtronger, that Gods mercy compaſſeth them about: for that which is but Miniſteriall in the Angells, is Primitive in God: and though the Miniſtery of Angells may bee: yet Gods mercy can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bee fruſtrate; and eſpecially when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth about; for then, neither troubles on the right hand, nor troubles on the left; neither tumours of Proſperity, nor grypings of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity: then neither troubles before them, nor troubles behind them; neither agonies of terrour, nor rackes of perſecution, ſhall ever come ſo neere them, as to touch them; at leaſt, not ſo prevaile againſt them, as to hurt them. That notwithſtanding all their troubles: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>11</label> It ſhall bee juſtly ſayd ſtill; <hi>Bee glad yee that are
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13931:41"/>righteous, and rejoyce in the Lord: ſhowte for joy, all yee that are upright of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And may it not bee as well ſayd to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: Bee glad, and ſhowte for joy? or rather have they not more cauſe of rejoycing, then the godly: The wicked indeed may rejoyce to ſee their full barnes and their full bags: but alas, what becomes of their joy, when they heare it ſayd; <hi>Stulte hac nocte repetent animam tuam?</hi> They may rejoyce to ſit with <hi>Belſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> at their full cups, in revelling and feaſting: but alas, what becomes of their rejoycing, when they ſee it written upon the wall before them, <hi>Mene, Tekel, Peres?</hi> All gladneſſe of the world is often converted, alwaies conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible into ſorrow: onely the gladneſſe that is in God, never ſuffers Ecclypſe. A ſingle kinde of joy the wicked may have, but becauſe their rejoycing is in the world, and not in God; they are farre, God knowes from ſhowting for joy. None but the righteous rejoyce in the Lord: and therefore none but the righteous can ſhowte for joy. This <hi>David</hi> did, when hee danced before the Arke: and this <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did; when <hi>Exultavit ut videret diem Demini:</hi> Hee leaped for joy, to ſee the day of Chriſt. Is there ſhowting for joy at Olympick games, where but a Garland is gotten perhaps of Bay, at moſt but of ſome fading matter: and ſhall their not bee ſhowting for joy, at the game of the great Olympus, where there wil be a crown gotten of glory, that ſhall never wither
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13931:42"/>nor fade away? O my ſoule, there will be the victory, that is onely worthy of ſhowting for joy: which as it is common to all the godly, ſo it is proper to onely the godly: who being upright in heart, and having their converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Heaven already, they ſee with cleerer eyes than <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw Chriſts day, the ſaints expecting them, the Angels ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them; and that which is more than the moſt that can be ſaid or thought, God himſefle preparing for them their ſeverall Manſions of Beatitude: that wee may juſtly conclude as we began; <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are forgiven, and whoſe ſins are covered; Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord imputeth no ſinne, and in whoſe Spirit there is no guile.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:13931:42"/>
            <head>THE THIRTIE EIGHTH PSALME.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> 
               <hi>Lord rebuke mee not in thine anger, neither chaſten mee in thy heavie diſpleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>For thine arrowes ſlicke faſt in mee; and thy hand preſſeth mee ſore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>There is no ſoundneſſe in my fleſh, becauſe of thine anger: neither is there any reſt in my bones, by reaſon of my ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>For mine iniquities are gone over my head, as an heavie burthen, they are too heavie for mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>My wounds ſtincke and are corrupt, becauſe of my fooliſhneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>I am troubled, I am bowed downe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; I goe mourning all the day-long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:13931:43"/> 7 <hi>For my bones are filled with a loathſome diſeaſe: and there is no ſoundneſſe in my fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>I am ſeeble and ſore broken: I have roared through the diſquietneſſe of my heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Lord, all my deſire is before thee; and my groaning is not hid from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>My heart panteth, my ſtrength faileth me; and as for the light of mine eyes, that alſo is gone from mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>My loversand friends ſtand aloofe from my ſore, and my kinſmen ſtand a farre off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>They alſo that ſeeke after my life lay ſnares for mee; and they that ſeeke my hurt, ſpeake miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous things, and imagine deceit all the day long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>But I as a deafe man heard not; and I was as a dambe man that openeth not his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Thus I was as a man that beareth not; and in whoſe mouth are no reproofes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>For in thee, O Lord, doe I hope: Thou wile heare mee, O Lord, my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>For I ſaid, Heare mee, leſt otherwiſe they ſhould reioyce over mee: when my foot ſlippeth, they magnifie themſelves againſt mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>For I am readie to halt, and my ſorrow is continually before mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>For I will declare mine iniquitie; I will be
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13931:43"/>ſorry for my ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>But mine enemies are lively, and they are ſtrong; and they that hate mee without cauſe, are multiplied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>They alſo that render evill for good, are mine adverſaries; becauſe I follow the thing that good is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>For ſake me not, O Lord, O my God, be not farre from mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>Make haſte to helpe mee, O Lord my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <head>MEDITATIONS upon the 38. Pſalme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ut is it not an abſurd requeſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>1</label> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire God, not to rebuke mee in his anger; as though I thought hee would rebuke mee if hee were not angry? Is it not a ſenſleſſe ſuite, to pray to God, not to chaſten mee in his diſpleaſure; as though hee would chaſten mee if hee were not diſpleaſed? The frowardeſt natures that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13931:44"/>are, will yet be quiet as long as they be pleaſ'd: and ſhall I have ſuch a thought, of the great, yet gracious God, that hee ſhould be pleaſ'd, and yet not bee quiet? But O my ſoule, Is it all one, to rebuke in his anger, and to rebuke when hee is angry? He may rebuke when hee is angry, and yet reſtraine and bridle in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: but to rebuke in his anger, is to let looſe the reines to his anger: and what is it to give the reines to his anger, but to make it out-run his mercy? and then what a miſerable caſe ſhould I bee in, to have his anger to aſſault me, and not his mercie readie to relieve mee? to have his in dignation fall upon mee, when his loving kindneſſe were not by to take it off? Oh therefore, rebuke mee not in thine anger, O God: but let thy rebuking ſtay for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; chaſten mee not in thy diſpleaſure, but let thy lovingkindneſſe have the keeping of thy rod.</p>
            <p>But though the requeſt be never ſo juſt; yet muſt it not needs be a weariſome thing to God, to have us alwaies come to him with the ſame petition, as though wee would perſecute him with importunity, and make him doe that, which he is not willing to doe? for if he were willing to grant it, hee would no doubt have done it before now; when in the ſixth <hi>Pſalme,</hi> we asked him as earneſtly for it, as we can doe in this. But O my ſoule, is importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity a fault? if it bee, it is a fault I ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee perſwaded ever to leave. Did Chriſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13931:44"/>count it a fault in the woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> who would take no anſwer; but ſtill cried after him, till hee granted her ſuite? Did not <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> importune God five times, about the ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>Sodome?</hi> and did not God grant as long as hee importun'd? And may wee not thinke that if hee had continued his importunity ſtill, hee might as well have gotten <hi>Sodome</hi> to bee ſpared for one mans ſake, as hee had done for ten? Is God like man, that the importunitie of ſuitours ſhould bee a trouble to him? Can wee thinke, that God ſhould bee diſpleaſed with our importunity to him, when he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to uſe importunity himſelfe to us? Did not God call to <hi>Samnel,</hi> three times one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; when hee bid him go to <hi>Eli,</hi> with a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage? Was it not importunity which Chriſt uſed to <hi>Peter,</hi> when thrice together hee asked him, <hi>Simon</hi> ſonne of <hi>Ionas,</hi> loveſt thou mee? Indeed <hi>Peter</hi> ſeemed not well pleaſ'd with this importunity: but God never was, never will bee found to bee diſpleaſed with it. Never therefore feare to bee importunatewith God; but feare rather, thou canſt never bee impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate enough; for ſo highly is God pleaſed, or rather indeed delighted with our importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in praying, that hee oftentimes denies the firſt ſuit of his ſervants, becauſe he would bee importun'd by a ſecond; oftentimes the ſecond, becauſe hee would have a third. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that which in ſuits to men is importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in ſuits to God is fervencie and perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13931:45"/>and ſeemes to reſemble the nature of the <hi>Seraphims;</hi> where ſingle prayer but of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Angels, of whom as ſome fell, ſo this may faile, and often doth, the other never.</p>
            <p>But though importunity bee to God moſt pleaſing alwaies: yet to us, it is then moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, when the cheerfull face of God is turned into frownes: and when there is a juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceived feare of the continuance of his anger: and have not I juſt cauſe to feare it, having the arrowes of his anger ſticking ſo faſt in mee? if hee had meant to make me but a Butt, at which to ſhoot his arrows; he would quickly, I ſuppoſe, have taken them up againe; but now that hee leaves them ſticking in mee, what can I think, but that he meanes to make mee his quiver; and then I may looke long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, before hee come to plucke them out. They are arrows indeed that are fethered with ſwiftneſſe, and headed with ſharpneſſe; and to give them a force in flying, they are ſhot, I may ſay, out of his Croſſe-bow, I am ſure his bow of croſſes: for no arrowes can flie ſo faſt, none pierce ſo deep, as the croſſes &amp; afflictions with which he hath ſurprized me: I may truly ſay ſurprized me; ſeeing when I thought my ſelf moſt ſafe, and ſaid, I ſhall never be moved even then theſe arrows of his anger lighted upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, and ſtick ſo faſt in my fleſh, that no arm but his that ſhot them, is ever able to draw them forth Oh then, as thou haſt ſtretched forth thine arme of anger, O God, to ſhoot theſe arrowes
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13931:45"/>at mee; So ſtretch forth thine arme of mercy, to draw them forth; that I may rather ſing Hymns, then Dyrges unto thee: and that thou maiſt ſhew thy power, as well in pardoning, as thou haſt done in condemning. I, alas, am as an Anvile under two hammers: one, of thine anger, another of my ſinne; both of them beating inceſſantly upon mee; the ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of thine anger, beating upon my fleſh, and making that unſound: the hammer of my ſin, beating upon my bones, and making them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet; although indeed both beat upon both: but thine anger more upon my fleſh, as being more ſenſible: my ſin more upon my bones, as being more obdurate. Gods anger and ſin, are the two efficient cauſes of all miſery; but the Procatarkticke cauſe indeed, is ſin: Gods anger, like the houſe that <hi>Sampſon</hi> pulled upon his own head, falls not upon us, but when we pull it upon our ſelves, by ſinne.</p>
            <p>I know by the unſoundneſſe of my fleſh, that God is angry with me: for if it were not for his anger, my fleſh would bee ſound: but what ſoundneſſe can be in it now, when Gods angry hand lies beating upon it continually, and never ceaſeth? I know by the unquietnes of my bones, that I have ſinne in my boſome; for if it were not for ſinne, my bones would bee quiet: But what quietneſſe can bee in them now, when ſin lies gnawing upon them inceſſantly, with the worme of remorſe? one would thinke my bones were farre enough re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13931:46"/>and cloſely enough hidden from ſins doing them any hurt: yet ſee the ſearching nature, the venemous poyſon of ſinne, which pierceth through my fleſh, and makes unqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe in my very bones.</p>
            <p>I know my fleſh is guilty of many faults, by which it juſtly deſerves unſoundneſſe: but what have my bones done? for they miniſter no fuell to the flames of my fleſhes ſenſuality; and why then ſhould they bee troubled? But are not my bones ſupporters of my fleſh, and are they not by this, at leaſt acceſſary to my fleſhes faults? as acceſſaries then, they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſame puniſhment the fleſh it ſelfe is, which is the principall.</p>
            <p>I cannot but wonder at this condition in my ſelfe: there is nothing I more loath then ſinne, yet nothing I more willingly embrace: nothing that I more abhorre, yet nothing I more readily entertaine: what mervaile then, if their bee unſoundneſſe in my fleſh, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe in my bones, when I will needes bee taking ſo turbulent a gueſt, ſo deadly a poyſon as ſinne is into my boſome? and make an idoll of that, which I know ſo well to bee a monſter?</p>
            <p>As a man that ſtands in the water, as long as it comes but to his middle, or but up to his ſhoulders, endures and beares it ſafty enough; but when it comes once to goe over his head, it then overwhelmes and preſently ſtrangles him: ſuch alas am I, my ſinne a long time,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13931:46"/>came I may ſay, but up to my ſhoulders; and then I thought my ſelfe ſafe enough; now God knowes, I am over head and eares in ſinne, and ſo overwhelmed with it, that my breath is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from mee, and I have not ſo much as any breath of Grace remaining in me. No ſtrength is ſo great, but it may be overburdened, though <hi>Sampſon</hi> went light away with the gates of <hi>Az<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah;</hi> yet when a whole houſe fell upon him, it cruſhed him to death. And ſuch, alas, am I, I have had ſin as a burden upon mee, ever ſince I was borne: but bore them a long time as light, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the gates of <hi>Azzah;</hi> but now that I have pulled a whole houſe of ſinne upon mee, how can I chuſe but be cruſhed to death with ſo great a weight? And cruſhed, O my Soule, thou ſhouldſt be indeed; if God for all his anger, did not take ſome pitty on thee: and for all his diſpleaſure, did not ſtay his hand from further chaſtening thee.</p>
            <p>I know, O Lord, I have done moſt fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to let my ſores runne ſo long, without ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for helpe: For now, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>My wounds ſtinke and are corrupt;</hi> in as ill a caſe as <hi>Lazarus</hi> body was, when it had beene foure daies buried; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make any man deſpaire, that did not know thee as I doe: For, doe not I know, that <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit tibi?</hi> doe not I know, thou haſt as well wiſedome to remedy my foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe, as power to cure my wounds? Could the grave hold <hi>Lazarus,</hi> when thou didſt but open thy mouth to call him forth? No more
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13931:47"/>can the corruption of my ſores, bee any hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to their healing, when thy pleaſure is to have them be cured. Although therfore I have done my owne diſcretion wrong to deferre my care; yet I will not doe thy power wrong, to deſpaire of thy cure: for, how ſhould I deſpair, who know thee to be as powerfull, as thou art mercifull; if I may not rather ſay, to bee as mercifull, as thou art powerfull: Each of them indeed an <hi>Abyſſus:</hi> and when <hi>Abyſſus Abyſſum vocat,</hi> what marvell, if their follow marvells?</p>
            <p>And as I do not deſpaire, ſo neither do I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>For I am troubled, I am bowed downe, and go mourning all the day long.</hi> I am troubled no leſſe with the griefe of thy diſpleaſure, then with the paine of my wounds: each of them alone, juſt cauſe of mourning; but both of them together, of mourning all the day long.</p>
            <p>I have told hertofore, how I ſpend my night: all the night I water my bed with teares. Now I tell how I ſpend my day; all the day long in mourning. And can it be, O God, thou ſhouldſt neither regard my weeping, nor my mourning? neither my weeping all night, nor my mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all day?</p>
            <p>If my fleſh had continued as God made it, there had been in it, both ſoundnes, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but alas, my ſinne, and his arrowes, his arrowes by reaſon of my ſin, have ſo wounded it, that it is nothing now, but a very Ciſtern of corruption: for all ſinne hath poyſon in it, and breedes diſeaſes; infinite diſeaſes in the Soule,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13931:47"/>loathſome diſeaſes in the bodie. And what will not diſeaſes doe in theſe bodies of ours? whoſe ſpirits can be ſo errect, but will bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected? whoſe limbes ſo ſtrong, but will bee bowed downe? whoſe heart ſo cheerefull, but will bee made to mourne with the violence of diſeaſes? And now therfore, <hi>am I dejected, I am bowed down, I gomourning all the day long</hi> and may I not ſay, with the worſt kinde of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the mourning perhaps of the chyne: like Horſe and Mule that have no underſtanding? <hi>For my loynes are filled with a loathſome diſeaſe:</hi> the very diſeaſe, that made <hi>Elias,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> and <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> to weare girdles of beaſts skins about their loynes; and they with wearing ſuch girdles, prevented in themſelves, the loathſomneſſe of this diſeaſe: but I, alas, never thought of any girdle, much leſſe of Beaſts skins: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the diſeaſe is now grown ſo loathſome up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee, that it hath filled my loynes; ſo filled them, that it hath not ſo much as a ſpare room left to make a perfume in; ſo loathſome, that it makes me fit for no company but Lazars, for no place but an Hoſpitall: for how ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers endure the ſtinch of my ſores, when I am not able to endure it my ſelfe? how much leſſe, O God, canſt thou endure it, whoſe pure ſenſe is ſenſible, even of that impurity, which is to us inſenſible, in the ſtarres themſelves? Thou, O God, didſt vouchſafe this favour to our firſt Parents, to make them garments of Beaſts skins to cover their nakedneſſe, and may wee
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13931:48"/>not be bold to think, that the Girdles of Beaſts skins, which <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> wore about their loynes, were alſo of thy making? Oh then vouchſafe, O God, to give me ſuch a gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to weare about my loynes; a girdle of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence &amp; true mortification; which though it cannot now, as in <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> it did, prevent the growth and loathſomneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence in mee: It may at leaſt, as in <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> reſtraine it, and make mee capable of being cured.</p>
            <p>And as I have not deſpaired, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> nor preſumed: ſo neither have I murmured nor repined at thy chaſtiſements: I acknowledge my ſelfe moſt worthy to ſuffer them, but moſt unable to bear them. I am dejected no leſſe in body, then in ſpirit; and yet though I could not ſpeake for weakneſſe, I have roured for griefe; and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes of my heart, hath ſupplied the feeble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my tongue. Indeed if I could have been a Boanerges, and have gotten a voice like thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I ſhould have uſed it now in ſpeaking to thee; that if my importunity before could not, at leaſt my loudneſſe now might prevaile with thee, to procure thee to hear me. <hi>For I am feeble and ſore broken, I have roared through the unqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes of my heart.</hi> All long of the unquietnes of my heart, and the unquietnes of my heart, all long of my ſin: for where ſin is, there will never be but unquietnes of heart, &amp; an unquiet heart will alwaies produce theſe miſerable effects: Feeblenes of body, dejectedneſſe of mind, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13931:48"/>roaring of voice.</p>
            <p>But how can roaring ſtand with feebleneſſe, which ſeemes to require a ſtrength of ſpirits? Is it not therefore a roaring, perhaps not ſo much in lowdneſſe, as in an inarticulate expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? that having done actions more like a beaſt then a man, I am forced to uſe a voice, not ſo much of a man, as of a beaſt? Or is it perhaps a roaring in ſpirit, which the heart may ſend forth, though the bodie bee feeble: or rather then moſt, when it is moſt feeble: not unlike the blaze of a Candle, then greateſt, when going out. Howſoever it be, this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; the heart is that unhappy plot of ground which receiving into it the accurſed ſeed of ſinne, brings forth in the bodie and ſoule of man, theſe miſerable fruits: and how then can I be free from theſe weedes of the fruits, that have received into me ſo great a meaſure of the ſeed? O vile ſinne, that I could as well avoid thee, as I can ſee thee; or could as eaſily reſiſt thee, as I deadly hate thee; I ſhould not then complaine of either feebleneſſe of bodie, or dejectedneſſe of mind, or roaring of voice: but I ſhould perfectly injoy that happie quietneſſe in all my parts, which thou, O God, didſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly beſtow as a bleſſed dowrie on our firſt Parents, at their creation. And now, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> O my ſoule, let mee aske thee a queſtion: Why art thou caſt downe, and why art thou diſquieted within mee? Hope thou in God; for I will yet praiſe him, who is the health of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13931:49"/>and my God. But what neede was thereof roaring? for what matter is it whether I ſpeake to God in a ſoft voice, or in a lowd? ſeeing thou knoweſt, O God, the very thoughts of my heart, <hi>and my groaning is not hid from thee.</hi> Though I ſpeake not, but onely thinke to ſpeake, yet thou knoweſt it: though I think not, but onely groane to think, yet thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it; and knowing theſe things, thou knoweſt O God, that my griefe is more for thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, then for my wounds: leſſe for the paine I feele of thine arrowes ſticking in mee, then for the unkindneſſe I take at thy ſhooting them at mee. As the love with which thou giveſt, is more deare to mee then thy gifts; ſo the anger with which thou ſtrikeſt, is more grievous to mee then thy rod: and alas, O Lord, how can I then chuſe but roare through the unquietnes of my heart, when I want both thy gifts, and thy love too, and yet feele thy rod, and thine anger too? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> 
               <hi>All my deſire, O Lord, is ever before thee, and my groaning is not hid from thee:</hi> but what availes it mee, that my deſire bee all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, if it be not all for thee? what avails it mee, that my groaning be not hid from thee, if it be not made to thee? If I deſire any thing beſides thee, that deſire is from weakneſſe, and then thou regardeſt it not; if I groane to any but thee, that groaning is from vainneſſe, and then thou ſeeſt it not: but now that my deſire is onely for thee, and my groaning onely to thee; now I know, thou both ſeeſt and regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13931:49"/>them; and I doubt not, O God, but mee for them.</p>
            <p>But, alas, O Lord, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>10</label> this is not yet the whole chapter of my miſery; for beſides this, <hi>My heart panteth, my ſtrength faileth mee; and as for the light of mine eyes, that alſo is gone from me.</hi> And what is my heart, but the foundation; what my ſtrength, but the pillars? what mine eies, but the windows of my building? If theſe then bee ruined, how can my whole building chuſe but bee demoliſhed? My heart is not wont to pant, but in ſome great agonie; nor my ſtrength to ſayle, but in ſome great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict; nor my ſight to goe from mee, but in ſome great diſaſter: how great then, alas, muſt my agonie bee, how hard my conflict, how grievous my diſaſter; when my heart, my ſtrength, my ſight, all ſayle mee at once? Though my heart panted, yet if my ſtrength continued, I ſhould have a ſupport: or though my ſtrength fayled, yet if my ſight continued, I ſhould have a guide: but when they all faile, and faile at once; alas, O Lord, how can I chuſe but fall, that have neither ſtrength to ſupport mee, nor eyes to guide mee: Thou, O God, muſt ſay to my heart, bee of good cheere: Thou muſt ſay to my ſtrength, I will bee thy fortreſſe: Thou muſt ſay to mine eies, I will be thy light: and then, and not till then, ſhall I ever have caſe, or confidence, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
            <p>It is ſome comfort to men in miſery, when
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13931:50"/>they have their friends about them; if not to relieve them, yet at leaſt to pitty them: for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven pitty, is a comfort to men in miſery: but ſo miſerable am I, that I am left alone, as one utterly forſaken. <hi>For even my lovers and friends ſtand aloofe from mee, and my kinſmen ſtand a farre off.</hi> They are all pieces that recoyle, and flie backe at the firſt voice of the powder. Yet it is not ſo much mee they ſtand aloofe from, as my ſore; for if it were not for my ſore, I ſhould have enough of their company, eaſily enough: but they cannot abide ſores, their eies are too tender to endure to ſee them, and yet hard enough, not to relieve them. Or is it they ſtand aloofe, that is ſo neere, as to ſhew, they are willing enough to ſee them; but yet ſo farre off, as to ſhew, they have no meaning to come and helpe them. But call you theſe lovers and friends? Men that flutter about us like flies, in the Summer of proſperity, but vaniſh and are gone in the winter of adverſity? Are friends but painted flowers, onely for ſhew, and nothing at all for uſe? Or if true flowers, yet onely to make noſegayes of, and never to make medicine of? Is there uſe of Phyſitians but when there are ſores; and when ſores come, will not they bee gotten to come? Is there uſe of friends, but in time of need; and when need comes, will they then bee gone? But alas, O Lord, was it not ſo with Chriſt himſelfe? company enough, friends enow, when there was no need; but as ſoone as <hi>Iudas</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:13931:50"/>comes with a band of men, ſcarſe a man found that will bee gotten to tarry: and if they uſed the Maſter ſo, can I that am a ſervant, looke to bee better uſed?</p>
            <p>But ſay, you call them friends, yet how can you call them lovers? for it is the nature of love, to bee readieſt at hand, when there bee troubles at hand. Doth not the Elme, alover of the Vine, ſupport the Vine, when it elſe would ſinke downe and fall to the ground? doth not the Vine ſtick cloſe to the Elme, and if the Elm chance to fall, chuſeth rather to fall with it, then to forſake it? And ſhall nature doe this in trees, and ſhall not reaſon, ſhall not vertue, do it much more in men? or ſhall trees bee reckoned the reaſonable Creatures, and men bee caſhiered out of the number? But this is the world; they are called lovers and friends, of their faces, no otherwiſe then Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boones may bee called men: for when a day of triall comes, they are often found as farre from friendſhip and true love, as Baboones from reaſon, and true underſtanding. And ſuch were my lovers and friends (alwaies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting <hi>Ionathan:</hi>) but I looked for better at my kinſmens hands: for there is in them a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquity of nature, and nature will hardly be kept from working: yet ſuch is my unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natneſſe, that in my behalfe, even nature her ſelfe growes idle, and I finde as little comfort from my kinſmen, as from my other lovers and friends: and to ſay truely, rather leſſe:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13931:51"/>
               <hi>for where my lovens and friends ſtand but aloofe, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>11</label> my kinſmen ſtand afarre off:</hi> neither of them neere indeed, but yet my kinſmen the fartheſt off: My lovers and friends ſtand but aloofe from my ſore, as taking it perhaps for a <hi>Noli me tangere;</hi> but my kinſmen ſtand afarre off, as taking it for no leſſe then the very plague. My lovers and friends ſtand aloofe from my ſore, as expecting perhaps a time of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very when they may come on againe; but my kinſmen ſtand afarre off, as never intending to hearken more after mee. My lovers and friends ſtand aloofe from my ſore, as fearing more my ſore then me, but my kinſmen ſtand a farre off, as fearing mee no leſſe then my ſore: and where my lovers and friends by ſtanding aloofe, doe but violate the law of a contracted friendſhip: My kinſmen by ſtanding afarre off, violate even the law of naturall affection: And is not this a grievous thing, that the law of reaſon, the law of friendſhip, the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall all bee broken, rather then I ſhall be relieved, or finde aſſiſtance? And now, O my ſoule, ſeeing thy lovers and friends, and kinſmen prove all unloyall, unfaithfull, and unnaturall, in whom alas canſt thou hope for helpe? In whom, O Lord, but onely in thee? for thou art a lover incomparably more loyall, then either the Vine to the Elme, or the Elme to the Vine: Thou are a friend infinitely more faithfull, then either <hi>Jonathan</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> or <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Ionathan;</hi> Thou art a kinſman, but
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13931:51"/>rather a father unſpeakably more tender of thy children, then either <hi>Boaz</hi> of <hi>Ruth;</hi> or <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> of his one and onely ſonne <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though to bee thus forſaken, rejected, and even abhorred, by lovers, and friends, and kinſmen, bee miſery enough, and more then enough for one man to beare; yet this is not all the miſery I beare, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>12</label> but <hi>they alſo that ſeek after my life lay ſnares for me: and they that ſeeke my hurt, ſpeake miſchievous things, and imagine deceit all the day long.</hi> Is it not enough that my friends and kinſmen will doe mee no good; but there are others that will doe mee hurt: and it is not enough, that they wiſh my hurt, but they ſeeke to do it; they hunt after mee, as after a prey: and it is no ſmall hurt they ſeeke to doe mee; but they lay ſnares for my life: nothing but my life will ſerve them; and they doe it not ſo much by open violence, which might perhaps bee withſtood; but they doe it by fraud and deceit, which is not eaſie to bee avoided: for firſt, they ſpeake miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous things, they raiſe ſcandalls, and worke the world to an ill opinion of mee; and then they lye deviſing of waies how to entrap mee; and they ſpend not an houre or two about it, but they imagine deceit all the day long. And alas, O Lord, is this a world to have ſafety in ſcandalls? where if ſome bee ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe them, others are as ready to believe them? If there bee a <hi>Iezabel</hi> to plot a falſe accuſation, are there not elders to put it in execution? and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13931:52"/>do I not in this ſtill runne in the ſame line with my Lord Chriſt Ieſus? For did not the ſcribes and Phariſees, firſt deviſe miſchievous things againſt him; and then the High-prieſts and Rulers believe what they deviſed, and execute what they believed? And what, O Lord, do I all this while? doe I ſtand upon my guard, and have an eye to their practiſes? doe I ſeeke to repell their violence by force, or to fruſtrate their fraud with circumſpection? Do I cleere their ſcandalls with apologies, or do I anſwer their clamours with vociferations? God knowes, none of all theſe: I neither uſe armes offenſive, nor defenſive; all my doing is ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and all the apology I make for my ſelfe, is ſilence; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>13</label> 
               <hi>For as a deafe man, I heard not, and as a dumbe man, I opened not my mouth:</hi> For why ſhould I hear, when I meant not to ſpeak? and why ſhould I ſpeake, when I knew before hand I ſhould not bee heard? I knew by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, I ſhould but provoke them, and make them more guilty, that were guilty too much before. I therefore thought it better my ſelfe to bee ſilent, then to ſet them a roaring, and make them grow outragious. No doubt, a great wiſedome in <hi>David,</hi> to know that, to be deaf and dumb was in this caſe his beſt courſe, but yet a farre greater vertue, that knowing it, hee was able to do it. O how happy ſhould we bee, if wee could alwaies doe that, which wee know is beſt to bee done: and if our wills were as readie to act, as our reaſon is able to enact,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13931:52"/>wee ſhould then decline many rocks wee now runne upon; wee ſhould then avoid many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours we now runne into. To bee deafe, and dumb, are indeed great inabilities and defects, when they bee naturall; but when they be vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, and I may ſay artificiall, they are then great abilities, or rather perfections. They are two ſtemmes, upon which do grow the excellent vertues of patience and charity; which though <hi>David</hi> ſhewed in himſelfe in a great meaſure, at the rayling of <hi>Shimei:</hi> yet he could never ſo properly ſpeake them of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as in the perſon of Chriſt: for of him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ſacred ſtory relates, that being ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon, and reviled, buffeted and beaten by the baſe multitude, yet as a ſheepe led to the ſlaughter, hee opened not his mouth, but was deafe and dumbe even to death.</p>
            <p>O grievous alteration! tranſcendent indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity! Hee that reſtored Creeples to health, and raiſed the dead to life; now to bee depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelfe of the chiefe faculties of life, both active and paſſive? He that made the deafe to heare, and the dumbe to ſpeake: now himſelf neither to ſpeake, nor heare? A grievous caſe no doubt to bee ſo: and yet no doubt, a juſt cauſe it ſhould bee ſo: for if he had heard, he ſhould have heard but blaſphemies: and if he had ſpoken, he muſt have ſpoken but reproofs: and ſeeing blaſphemies were too prophane for his ſacred ears to hear, and reproofs too harſh for his milde tongue to utter: what marvell,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13931:53"/>if he that made the care, did himſelfe not hear, what marvell, if hee that was the Word it ſelf, did not ſpeake a word?</p>
            <p>And as my deafeneſſe and dumbeneſſe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>15</label> have not proceeded from imbecillity, but from pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; ſo neither have they proceeded from feare, but from reverence: for why ſhould I ſpeake, when my hope is in thee, O God, that thou wilt ſpeak: why ſhould I hear, when thou wilt heare for mee? For alas, O Lord, when I hear, they ſpeak what they liſt, as either think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I cannot controll them or not caring whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I can or no: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou heareſt, they are glad to take heed what they ſay; for thou haſt ſcales to weigh their words, and if find them light, power to cenſure them. Why then ſhould I offer to hear or ſpeak, when I know ere long I ſhall have a hearing before thee, where thou ſhalt bee their judge, and wilt be my advocate. And have I not reaſon, till then, to conſecrate my eares and tongue to thee? It is true, inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious language is a provocation able to make a dumbe man to ſpeake, and I may ſay, able to looſen the tongue of <hi>Croeſus</hi> his dumbe ſonne: but he that ſo provoked, ſhould fall a ſpeaking, were very like to fall in ſpeaking: for it is a ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery argument to be ſpoken in: and if in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I ſhould ſlip never ſo little, Oh what a joy it would bee to my enemies, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſire better ſport, they would magnifie themſelves againſt mee: I ſhould be their blind <hi>Sampſon</hi> to make them merry, I ſhould ſerve
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13931:53"/>them for a ſtocke of deriſion. Oh therefore, ſuffer mee not, O God, to ſuffer theſe indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but do thou heare for me, do thou ſpeak for mee: <hi>for I alas, am readie to halt, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> and my ſorrow is continually before mee,</hi> that if my ſlipping and falling, bee a cauſe to make mine enemies rejoyce, they may bee ſure of joy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: for how can I chuſe but often fall, that am of my ſelfe ſo readie to halt? and ſpecially when my ſorrow is alwaies before mee; that makes me I cannot ſee my way before me; for what doth more blind the eyes, and take away the ſight, then ſorrow? Was it not ſorrow that hindred <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> from diſcerning Chriſt, when ſhee ſaw him at the Sepulchre? And beſides, my halting is the worſt kinde of halting that is; for I come not to it, as <hi>Iacob</hi> came to his, by wraſtling with an Angell, which brought a bleſſing with it: but I come to it as <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> did, by the imbecillity or inequalitie of my parts: For having two feete to goe upon, my reaſon, and my will; how can I chuſe but halt, when my will is ſo much longer then my reaſon? and then, if to the apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my falling, by reaſon of my halting, there bee added the inadvertency of the way, by reaſon of my ſorrow: how can I chuſe but even trip at every ſtep I take? that if mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies rejoyce at my fallings, they are very like to have their fill of rejoycing; for if a juſt man fall ſeven times a day, how often, alas; am I like to fall, that halt, I may rightly ſay, down
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13931:54"/>right in ſinne? but let mine enemies rejoyce to ſee mee fall as much as they pleaſe; this ſhall not hinder mee from ſeeking to riſe: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no riſing from ſin, but by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing it; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>18</label> 
               <hi>I will therefore declare mine iniquitie, I will bee ſorry for my ſinne:</hi> I will declare mine iniquity, that my enemies may ſee, I can ſpeak to God, though I was dumbe to them; and I will bee ſorry for my ſinne, to make them ſee how little I envie their rejoycing, that can take pleaſure in my own ſorrowing: for to declare mine iniquities without ſorrowing for my ſin, might rather bee thought an oſtentation then a penitence, and rather ſhew mee proud of my ſinne, then aſhamed of it. I will therefore bee ſorry for my ſinne, that my ſorrow may teſtifie for me, that my declaration now is out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition; as my declaration ſhall teſtifie, that my dumbneſſe before, was out of compaſſion. But though I ſcorn mine enemies deriding, yet I am not inſenſible of mine owne diſgrace: and therefore hope that my ſpeaking now, ſhall ſupply my dumbneſſe before; and make thee, O God, to take my cauſe into thine owne hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; and either convert mine enemies, or elſe confound them. This indeed is my hope, though I ſee as yet but ſmall fruit of my hope; <hi>For mine enemies are lively and ſtrong, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>19</label> and they that hate mee without a cauſe are multiplied.</hi> I looked for abatement of their rejoycing, and they continue lively ſtill: for abatement of their power, and they continue as ſtrong as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13931:54"/>for abatement of their number, and they are rather multiplied, and increaſe. But though it bee an eaſie matter for them to be lively, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſtrong as they are; and to bee ſtrong; being ſo many as they are: yet how eaſie is it for thee, O God, by thy Spirit of life, to ſtrike a dump into their livelineſſe; by thy Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, to ſuppreſſe their ſtrength; by thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiteneſſe, to confound their number: and why then ſhould I bee afraid what mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies can doe unto mee? why ſhould I bee frighted with an arm of fleſh? But that which is moſt ſtrange of all, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>20</label> they hate mee without a cauſe: as if one ſhould ſay; Their hatred to mee is miraculous: an effect, without a cauſe: for what cauſe of hatred, where ſuch motives of love? I ſeeke to doe them good, I follow the thing that is good, and yet they hate mee. And yet this is no wonder, for is it not ſayd, <hi>Qui male agit, odit lucem?</hi> They that do evill hate the light? and if hate the light, how can they chuſe but hate the children of light? That it appeares to bee cauſe enough to the wicked, to hate the godly, if they diſcerne in them but any ſparkes of godlineſſe: and then if this bee the caſe, that I muſt either be wicked my ſelfe, or elſe bee hated of the wicked: I ſhall never ſtand long in making my choice, ſeeing I ſhall never certainly buy their love ſo deere. But ſince they are generations of vipers, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mee evill for good: at leaſt, O Lord, doe not thou forſake mee; be not thou farre from
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13931:55"/>mee: for as long as thou art on my ſide, and ſtayeſt by mee, what though the waters roare, and the mountaines ſhake with the ſwelling therof? What though the bulls of <hi>Baſan</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeme, and the ſtrong bulls be ſet me round: ſeeing thou art able to deliver mee from their fury, and from the hands of all that hate me.</p>
            <p>But O my ſoule, thou maiſt call long enough to God, not to bee farre from thee, and all in vaine, if thou bee farre from him. Take heed therefore, it bee not found true in thee, which hee ſometimes ſayd: <hi>This people draweth neere mee with their lips, but their hearts are far from mee:</hi> for if thou bee neere him onely with thy lips, ſuch neereneſſe will do thee ſmall good: it is not the neighbourhood of lips that hee cares for: but if thou wilt have him not to be farre from thee, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>22</label> thou muſt bee carefull that thy heart be not farre from him. And yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this enough, O God, that thou bee not farre from me, if thou ſtand but onely looking on, and makeſt not haſte to helpe me: Thy ſlowneſſe may bee as prejudiciall to mee, as thy being farre off: for alas, mine enemies are ready to devoure mee, and they that ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my ſoule, make haſte. Doe thou therefore, O God, make haſte alſo, &amp; be not ſlower then mine enemies: neither let thy love, be out-run by their hatred. But O my ſoul, why ſhouldſt thou require God to make ſuch haſte, as though thou wouldſt as it were ſurprize him on a ſuddaine? Alas, is God like man, that hee
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13931:55"/>ſhould ſtand in need of time to conſider? Are there <hi>Secundae cogitationes</hi> with him, as there are with men? Is there any thing that can be ſuddaine, or unlookt for to him? Although therefore hee bee ſlow to anger, yet hee is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſlow to mercy; but for ſhewing of mercy, hee hath the wings of a Dove, and rides upon the winde. And ſeeing, O God, thou art able and canſt doe it; O ſhew thy ſelfe willing alſo, and be forward to doe it: Make haſte to help me, O Lord my ſalvation: Make haſte to helpe me, that thou maiſt be Lord of my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; leſt I fall into mine enemies hands, that would be lords of my deſtruction: or rather, make haſte to helpe me, O Lord, Thou that art my ſalvation: for untill thou come, I am, alas, a ſervant of ſin, and a bondſlave to Sathan, that would bee my deſtruction.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
